<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of some among our selves against the false principles of Dr. Sherlock in a letter to the doctor, occasioned by the sermon which he preached at the Temple-Church on the 29th of May, 1692 : in which letter are also contained reflexions on some other of the doctor's sermons, published since he took the oath.</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6402</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12706665</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12706665</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 357:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of some among our selves against the false principles of Dr. Sherlock in a letter to the doctor, occasioned by the sermon which he preached at the Temple-Church on the 29th of May, 1692 : in which letter are also contained reflexions on some other of the doctor's sermons, published since he took the oath.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by George Hickes. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 51.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Sermon preached at the Temple-Church, May 29, 1692.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF Some among Our Selves AGAINST THE <hi>Falſe Principles</hi> OF Dr. SHERLOCK.</p>
            <p>In a Letter to the Doctor, occaſioned by the Sermon which he preached at the <hi>Temple</hi>-Church, on the 29th of <hi>May,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>In which Letter are alſo contained Reflexions on ſome other of the Doctor's Sermons, publiſhed ſince he took the Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful the Maſters of the Bench of the Inner-Temple.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the general Opinion of the World, That you deſired your Maſter to publiſh the Sermon which he preached before you on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> that the Doctrine he delivered in it might come to publick Trial, and excite <hi>ſome among our ſelves</hi> to give it a publick Refutation. Having little to do this long Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I thought it would help away the time to write my own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon it in form of an Anſwer; and ſuch as it is I humbly preſent it to you, deſiring no other Favour from you, than that you would pleaſe to read it over, if it ſcape the Inquiſitors of the Preſs, and happen to get abroad. Your Study and Profeſſion is the Law, and it is the Defence of <hi>Law,</hi> and of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which is founded on <hi>Law,</hi> that I have undertaken against the Doctor, of whom in the following Diſcourſe I have here and there given ſome Account, as well as of his Principles, that the World may judge of both.<note place="margin">Ld. Chancellor <hi>Elleſmere</hi> in his Speech touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Poſtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> p. 33.</note> A great and eminent <hi>Lawyer</hi> divides the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi> into Three Parts; the First of which reſpects the <hi>Church,</hi> and it is called, <hi>Lex Eccleſiae;</hi> the Second reſpects the <hi>Crown,</hi> and is called, <hi>Lex Coronae;</hi> the Third reſpects the <hi>Subjects</hi> in Common, and it is called, <hi>Lex Terrae:</hi> And if <hi>Providential Poſſeſſion,</hi> according to your Maſter's Doctrine, can ſuperſede the ſecond part of the Law, and contrary to it give an Uſurper a <hi>Divine Right</hi> to the Crown, and all the Poſſeſsions, Authority, and Prerogatives that belong unto it; then I do not ſee but it muſt in like manner ſuperſede the other two parts alſo; and by conſequence give a Divine Right to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:66038:3"/> if he can recover Poſſeſſion of it; and the King himſelf a Divine Right to the Eſtates, and other Rights of the People, if he can get Poſſeſſion of them. I believe it will not pleaſe the Reverend Doctor to ſee his Doctrine improved into theſe Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; not only becauſe they are diſpleaſing to others, but ungrateful to himſelf, who hath a very tender regard to his own Rights, both as a Church-man and a Subject, though he make ſo light of thoſe of the Crown. But, Gentlemen, I am not here to diſpute againſt him, but by the Dedication of the following Treatiſe to teſtifie to the World the great Zeal I have for Law and Juſtice, and the great Eſteem I have for you, as Profeſſors of the one, and Patrons of the other; and that I am upon both Accounts,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THE Reader is deſired to take Notice, that in the Margin of the following Diſcourſe</p>
            <p>
               <hi>a. Signifies,</hi> An Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, entitled Obedience and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the preſent Government demonſtrated from Biſhop <hi>Ove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi>'s Convocation-Book, with a Poſtſcript.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>aa.</hi> An Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindication of the Caſe of Allegiance due to Sovereign princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>aaa.</hi> An Anſwer to a Letter to Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> written in Vindication of that part of <hi>Joſephus</hi>'s Hiſtory which gives the Account of <hi>Jaddus</hi>'s Submiſſion to <hi>Alexander,</hi> againſt the Anſwer to the Piece entituled <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the Preſent Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>b.</hi> The Title of an Uſurper after a thorough Settlement examined, in Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe of Allegiance due to Sovereign Powers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>c.</hi> The Duty of Allegiance ſettled upon its true Grounds, according to Scripture, Reaſon, and the Opinion of the Church, in Anſwer to a late Book of Dr. <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> entituled <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance due to Sovereign Powers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>d.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe of Allegiance conſidered, with ſome Remarks upon his Vindication.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>e.</hi> An Examination of the Arguments drawn from Scripture and Reaſon in Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe of Allegiance, and his Vindication of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>f. ſ.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Faſt Sermon before the Queen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>f.</hi> Precept and Providence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>g.</hi> Caſe of Allegiance to a King in Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>h.</hi> Great <hi>Britain</hi>'s Juſt Complaints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ In Sect. 13. <hi>ſignifies</hi> Reverſe.</p>
            <p>℞℞ In the ſame Sect. <hi>ſignifies</hi> Reverſes.</p>
            <p>xxx. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Sermon preached on the 30th of <hi>January</hi> before the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>xxix. His Sermon preached in the <hi>Temple</hi> Church on the 29th. of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Reader may be pleaſed to obſerve, that this Book, written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Sermon preached at the <hi>Temple</hi> Church on the 29th of <hi>May</hi> laſt, is alſo a full Anſwer to the greateſt part of Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s ſcandalous Sermon lately preached at <hi>Whitehall</hi> on the 27th of <hi>October,</hi> and ſince publiſhed by him under the Character of <hi>John</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> THE Maſters of the Bench of the <hi>Middle Temple</hi> did not concurr with the Maſters of the Bench of the <hi>Inner Temple,</hi> in deſiring Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> to print his Sermon. A Cenſure of ſome of his late Sermons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Diſagreement betwixt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> in his <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> and in his Sermon preached on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> before the Houſe of Commons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> betraid the Doctrine of Nonreſiſtance in his Sermon before the Houſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s new way of preaching againſt Rebellion prejudicial to all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, eſpecially in looſe and diſcontented Times.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s undecent Flatteries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The diſtinction betwixt God's Permiſſion and Appointment the beſt Cure of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Amazement at Providence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at his landing no Prince, according to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Principles. He is offended at the Bp. of <hi>London,</hi> for the Speech which he made to the Prince at St. <hi>James</hi>'s. He wrote an Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Enquiry into the preſent State of Affairs; Himſelf confuted out of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Providential Right as tottering a Foundation of the Monarchy as that of the Power of the People. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> bewailed the Silence and Paſſiveneſs of the Clergy at the time of the Revolution. How much he is altered as to his Opinion of Perſecution. He put the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> upon making his death-bed Declaration. Several of his Sayings. His Profeſſion or Proteſtation of Loyalty to her Majeſty by the laſt Judgment, not reconcilable with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Principles.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Juſtice as well as Charity and Fervency neceſſary to make Prayers acceptable to God. Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi>'s Jewiſh Hypocriſie commended.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10, 11, 12.</hi> The Reaſonings of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Adverſaries not contradictory to the general Senſe of Mankind, proved by the Authority of moſt learned, wiſe, and ſober Men, eſpecially of our own Nation, containing a particular account of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s former Opinion and Practice, and ſome account of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. The Practice of Men to be tried by Principles; the great Majority commonly in the wrong in times of Tryal and Perſecution, eſpecially in corrupt and looſe Ages.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:66038:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Arguments for praying for illegal as well as legal Kings exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and refuted. His <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> turned upon himſelf. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour under whom the Apoſtle wrote, whoever he was, proved to be a lawfull Emperour from the Roman Coines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Queſtions about Certainty plainly anſwered. A threefold diſtinction of Eſtates. His Queſtions about Certainty turned upon himſelf.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s undecent way of Reflecting upon the French King not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his former Maxim by which he rebuked Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi> An Apology for that King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> upbraiding King <hi>James</hi> with his misfortunes. How God hath upheld and comforted him in his misfortunes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> How paraſitically the Doctour hath magnified our late Victory at Sea. A ſhort account of ſome naval Victories in former times.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s former Opinion of our Deliverance. An Apology for thoſe Engliſh Proteſtants whom he falſly and ſlanderouſſy charges with inviting the <hi>French</hi> to conquer us. The true Reaſon of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s preſent Hatred to the <hi>French;</hi> Of Perſecution. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> exhorted to view his own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings before he dies. The World expects it from him.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:66038:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66038:5"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF Some among Our Selves AGAINST THE <hi>Falſe Principles</hi> OF Dr. SHERLOCK.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. TO juſtifie the Publication of your late Sermon at the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> you tell us in the firſt Period of the <hi>Dedication,</hi> that the Reader <hi>will perceive</hi> it was not intended for the Preſs; but if you had told us, that the Reader <hi>will perceive</hi> it was not fit for the Preſs, you had told us a more ſenſible Truth, which every ordinary Reader may perceive; but it is not ſo plain and perceivable a thing that you <hi>did not intend it for the Preſs;</hi> for you know, Sir, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are very ſecret things, and the many wretched pieces you have Printed ſince you took the Oath, and pitiful <hi>Sermons</hi> among the reſt, make us call your Non-intentions to print this, as well as your Judgment for printing it, into queſtion; for the World knows that you have a great ſhare of Love for your ſelf, and a good Opinion of your own Productions; and whether you only did not intend, or which is more, did intend not to print it, we cannot believe; but your own good Opinion of it, as well as that of the <hi>Bench,</hi> was a great motive to the Publication, or elſe the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the <hi>Middle-Temple Bench</hi> to concur with the deſire of that of the <hi>Inner-Temple,</hi> would in prudence have obliged you to a modeſt Non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance. I aſſure you, ſome who bear you no ill will, think they were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66038:6"/> much more your Friends in not deſiring you to Publiſh it; for how well ſoever it might be lik'd in Preaching, it appears ſo ill in Print, that many Men think the <hi>Bench</hi> of the <hi>Inner-Temple,</hi> or at leaſt the firſt makers of the motion among them, deſired you to print it to expoſe both it and you. I have very good reaſon alſo to believe that ſome of the Honourable Houſe had that deſign in deſiring you to print the Sermon which you Preached before them on the 30th of <hi>January</hi> laſt; for one who was at the making of the Order, deſpiſed you for your Flatteries in it, and ſaid, he could not when he heard it, but think of <hi>Mammon</hi> in <hi>Ben. Johnſon</hi>'s <hi>Alchymiſt,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>My Flatterers ſhall be the pure and gravest of Divines, that I can get for Money:</hi> Another ſaid, he concurred with the Order, becauſe he knew the Sermon would expoſe you; and to mention no more, a third ſaid to a Friend, that he was going with the Order of the Houſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> againſt his own Judgment. Sir, It is a ſad <hi>Dilemma</hi> that <hi>ſome Men,</hi> to ſpeak in your figure, bring the Honourable Houſe to, by their wretched Sermons, when Order or no Order will expoſe the Preacher; and which of the two would have moſt expoſed you, <hi>no deſire to Print, or to Print at their deſire,</hi> any Man that has leſs fondneſs for your performances, than your ſelf, may eaſily determine.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Caſe of Alleg. to Sovereign Powers.</note>2. All the World knows you wrote a Book to prove, that <hi>the full Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of a Crown gives the Poſſeſſor a Divine Right to it by Providence; and that this Right of Providential Poſſeſſion ought to take place of Legal Right, and carry the Subjects Allegiance from the Legal to the Providential King;</hi> and it is well known you choſe this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> becauſe you did not approve of that of <hi>Abdication,</hi> and <hi>Vacancy,</hi> upon which the <hi>Convention</hi> proceeded; and yet in this Sermon to the Houſe, you ſervilely juſtifie the Revolution upon the Principles of <hi>Abdication</hi> and <hi>Vacancy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 21, 22.</note> which ſuperſedes your Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencial Right by Poſſeſſion, as much as that in your account ſuperſedes a Right by Law. Thus, Sir, we have you in your <hi>Sermon before the Houſe</hi> Preaching againſt your ſelf, and your Reaſons in the <hi>Caſe of Allegiance:</hi> for in this you ſet <hi>their Majeſties</hi> Right to the Crown on the <hi>Baſis</hi> of pure Providential Poſſeſſion; but in that it ſtands upon the Legal foot of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> and <hi>Vacancy;</hi> for whether the Throne was vacant, or not vacant, <hi>fell under the Cognizance of the Eſtates; they were the ſole and proper Judges of it; and private Subjects, whatever their private Opinions were, were bound to acquieſce in the deciſion of the Caſe, which ought to determine the Conſciences of private Subjects;</hi> and yet, as I ſhall ſhew anon, you were far from acquieſcing in their deciſion, or having your Conſcience determined by it, for almoſt two years after it was, as it was determined by them: For ſo long time you had not diſcovered the <hi>Fundamental Reaſons of Government,</hi> which oblige private Subjects to acquieſce in their deciſion; nor did the fear <hi>of falling into Anarchy and Confuſion</hi> yet affect you; nor do I believe you would have thought on thoſe two Arguments to this day, had you not been to Preach <hi>before the Houſe of Commons,</hi> which never did, nor ever will like your Doctrine of Provdience: But you were to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which you thought would pleaſe them, and many of them ſmiled
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66038:6"/> to hear you contradict your ſelf to flatter them, and deſpiſed you for it; and it ſince came to be a diſpute among your Readers, whether in that Sermon you flattered the Honourable Houſe, or their Majeſties moſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Reaſon why you choſe the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of Providential Right, was for the ſake of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> which upon that <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is ſo cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly convey'd, without any contradiction to your <hi>Caſe of Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> from the Legal to the Providential King. This ſecret I had from one to whom you ſpoke freely on that Subject, about the time you were writing your <hi>Caſe of Allegiance;</hi> but in this Sermon, becauſe a great part of the Houſe love not the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> you have betraid that alſo, in ſaying,<note place="margin">P. 6.</note> 
               <hi>That you would not diſpute the lawfulneſs of Reſiſting the King's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, whether it were lawfull for the Parliament to take Arms againſt the King;</hi> and by ſuppoſing in the next Paragraph, <hi>That it was lawfull in a limitted Monarchy:</hi> But is this the way of arguing againſt <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> which not long ago was ſuch a damnable ſin, eſpecially on the 30th of <hi>January?</hi> I proteſt to you, Dr. ſhould I hear you ſpeak at this tender rate from the Pulpit againſt Adultery, I ſhould think you had a deſign upon ſome Ladies in the Congregation, and that you intended they ſhould underſtand by you that you thought it no ſin. Formerly on the 30th of <hi>January, Reſiſtance</hi> was a moſt damnable ſin, and the Doctrine of it Popiſh, Diabolical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the ſin of the day was the Murder of a King; but now it ſeems, Dr. <hi>you will not diſpute the lawfulneſs of reſiſting the King,</hi> it may be lawfull for any thing you know to the contrary, even on the 30th of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary;</hi> the ſin of which day now it ſeems,<note place="margin">P. 19.</note> lies in the Murder of a <hi>Good King, who kept the Laws, and was a Zealous Patron of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>of a King of ſuch Virtues, as are rarely found in meaner Perſons; nay, which would have adorned an Hermet's Cell:</hi> But had he been a King that had broken the Laws, and ſtretch'd his Prerogative to ſet up an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Commiſſion againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then the killing of him had been no Murder, at leaſt no ſuch barbarous Murder: But, Dr. at this rate of Preaching on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> Kings and Queens had need take care of themſelves; for I do not ſee but they are upon their Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Quam diu bene ſe geſſerint,</hi> and do not break the Laws; but if they do ſo, let them do it at their peril:<note place="margin">xxix p. 21.</note> For <hi>every irregularity in their motions is ſoon felt, and cauſes very fatal Convulſions in the State;</hi> or as a much better Subject ſaid by way of Apology for <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>There is no time paſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his Works, p. 28.</note> 
               <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor will there be time to come, ſo long as Men manage the Laws, but the Laws will be broken more or leſs.</hi>— So, Dr. in your <hi>Temple-Sermon</hi> to exhort us to pray for Kings, you tell us, <hi>That it is very difficult to govern a Family,</hi>
               <note place="margin">xxix. p. 24, 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>and that Princes are liable to miſtakes like other Men,</hi> and <hi>that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to miſinformations by Court-Flatterers, and ſubject to greater Temptations than other Men:</hi> But, Dr. If it be lawfull to take up Arms againſt the King in a limitted Monarchy, which you were contented to ſuppoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Houſe, and others of your Brethren plainly aſſert; then God help Kings of ſuch Monarchies,<note place="margin">xxx. p. 23.</note> eſpecially <hi>where the Springs and Fountains of Government are poyſoned, and where the Nation is already divided into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66038:7"/> Parties, both in Church and State:</hi> Such Kings, be they by Providence only, or Law and Providence together, it matters not, they had need look to their hits, when their beſt pretended Friends are willing to ſuppoſe it is lawfull to take up Arms againſt them. All your Apologies and Panegyricks upon their Majeſties, and Exhortations to pray for them, can never make them amends for ſuch a ſuppoſition; and they muſt indeed ſtand in need of more, and better Prayers than yours, if they have no better a Title to the Crown than that of Poſſeſſion, which you have found out for them; and that too no longer than <hi>they keep the Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe, Dr. to uſe your own Language, <hi>are very looſe Notions of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Obedience,</hi> and dangerous at ſuch a time as this, when ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Malecontents in both Kingdoms complain of the breach of Laws.<note place="margin">See <hi>h.</hi>
               </note> If you will go to <hi>Scotland,</hi> you ſhall hear two ſort of diſcontented Men cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour loudly againſt the Government, the <hi>Jacobite Epiſcoparians,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> the latter are ſo impudent, as to charge King <hi>William</hi> down right with the breach of the Original Contract; and the former complain of torturing Strangers againſt Law and the Articles of Government; of exerciſing illegal and unheard of Severities upon the complying Clergy, worſe than Dragooning; of aboliſhing Epiſcopacy, and thereby altering the Conſtitution of the Government; and of the Murder and Maſſacre of a Laird and his Clan in cold blood, after they had laid down their Arms, and ſubmitted to the Government. And you cannot be ignorant of the Complaints which are made at home, by reſtleſs and diſaffected Spirits, of pretended, Illegal, and Arbitrary Commitments of Men for High Treaſon; and, not to mention the Reflections which have been made in and out of Parliament upon Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Trial, you cannot but hear what a din this grumbling and diſaffected Faction make of exceſſive Fines, and Bail; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as they clamour, to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, and the Articles of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: And they bring one Example, among others, of a poor Boy, about thirteen years old, who was Arraign'd and Try'd at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> and condemned to the Pillory, and after he endured this Diſcipline and many other cruel hardſhips, was Fined at the Court of the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> above threeſcore times more than he and his Parents are worth. Sir, Theſe things conſidered, you ſhould have thundered with your old Zeal, and demonſtrations againſt Reſiſtance, as a damnable ſin, and taught Submiſſion and Obedience to their Majeſties upon the account of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Character, and not purely upon the account of their Virtues, as you uſed to do in former Sermons: And let me tell you, Dr. that the moſt effectual way of ſerving their Majeſties in the Pulpit, and eſpecially on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> is to Preach up the unconditional Duty of Subjects to Kings as Kings,<note place="margin">xxx. p. 23.</note> whether they be good or bad. This was the <hi>Strict Loyalty and Obedience, which you tell us was ſo earneſtly preſſed on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men before the Revolution, and made the People ſo paſſive in it:</hi> But by your favour Dr. not ſo paſſive; for, not to put you in mind of the vaſt numbers in the <hi>Weſt</hi> and the <hi>North,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Sherlock</hi> her ſelf, ſent in a Man and Horſe to the aſſiſtance of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and whether it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66038:7"/> was with your Connivance or Approbation, God and your own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can beſt tell.</p>
            <p>But however that was, this is certain, that it is moſt for the Intereſt of Princes, as well as moſt becoming Divines, to ſet the King as a King and not as an Hero before the People; and to convince their Conſciences of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Duty which reſults from their relation to him as <hi>Subjects,</hi> inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant of his moral Qualities; but the other way of Preaching which you have taken up, ſerves only to beget a precarious and doubtful ſenſe of Duty in the People, who, as your Sermon before the Houſe ſhews, can ſoon be made to have the worſt Opinion of the beſt of <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Sanderſons</hi> and <hi>Hammonds</hi> of former times, who guarded the Pulpit from all ſuſpicion of Flattery, would never have Preached ſo much in commendation of their Royal Maſters, as you have Preached in the praiſe of their Majeſties before their Faces, without any regard to their Modeſty, which is undoubtedly as great as any of their other Virtues. But ſince you took the Oath, it hath been a great part of your Study and Employment to write <hi>Panegyricks</hi> on them, and <hi>Satyrs</hi> againſt their Father, whereof the true reaſon was long ſince obſerved upon another occaſion by <hi>Aeneus Sylvius,</hi> which is this; That the Providential <hi>King</hi> in Poſſeſſion hath Biſhopricks and Deanries at his diſpoſal, but the Legal <hi>King</hi> out of Poſſeſſion hath nothing to beſtow.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is yet another paſſage in your Sermon before the Houſe, which I beg you to reflect upon, it is in the tenth page, where you ſay, that <hi>it is an amazing Providence, that God ſhould expoſe the greateſt Example of Piety and Virtue that had ſat upon the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Throne, to ſuch Indignities and Sufferings.</hi> Indeed, Sir, according to your new Doctrine, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the diſtinction betwixt God's permiſſion and appointment; a Man may be overwhelmed with amazement to think that God ſhould ſo expoſe him; but it is no ſuch matter of amazement to a Maſter in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to think he ſhould ſuffer, or permit them to be ſo expoſed, according to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Doctrine which you formerly taught in a Sermon entitled, <hi>Some ſeaſonable Reflections on the late Plot.</hi> There you tell us in the 11. page, <hi>That although God doth many times permit things to be done, (or elſe no Man could ever be guilty of any ſin) yet his forbidding it, is an argument he doth not approve of it, and no Man can reaſonably expect ſucceſs in Plotting againſt his Prince, but he who certainly knows, that God for</hi> ſome wiſe ends, and hidden reaſons will ſuffer <hi>ſuch a villany to take effect, which no Man can</hi> know without a Revelation. You Printed this Sermon ſince you publiſhed your <hi>Caſe of Non-reſiſtance,</hi> by which you truly proved by this diſtinction, that <hi>Athaliah</hi> and <hi>Nuncle Cromwel</hi> were not the Ordinance of God; and unleſs you fly to this diſtinction again, you will never get out of your amazement; but if you retreat to the Sanctuary of this old diſtinction, you will be able to unfold the Myſtery of Providence, and ſolve the difficulties of it in ſuch hard caſes as that of the Royal Martyr, where God for wiſe Reaſons of his own, doth only ſuffer Rebels and Regicides to ſucceed in their wicked deſigns, but he doth not approve of what they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66038:8"/> do, nor declare by the events of his Providence, that he orders, appoints, or authorizes whot is done by them. Were that ſo indeed, as you teach in your <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> and ſuppoſe to be true in your <hi>Temple Sermon,</hi> a Man might well be amazed, and perplexed into a Labyrinth of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and abſurdities, and, to rid his mind of them, be tempted rather to think there was no God: But this diſtinction removes all perplexities, and ſets the mind at eaſe and freedom: And, Dr. I appeal to your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if it doth not often obtrude it ſelf upon your thoughts, ſince you diſclaimed it; and whether your Underſtanding, ſo perplexed with amazing Providences, is not often ready to embrace it whether you will or no? Indeed it overthrows the whole Fabrick of your <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their Majeſties upon the Providential <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> but your learned Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have made it good againſt you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>e.</hi> from p. 5. to p. 15. <hi>b.</hi> from p. 32. to p. 39. <hi>c.</hi> ch. p. 6. <hi>d.</hi> from p. 62. to p. 82.</note> and before you Preach up the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right of Providence again, read the places in them cited in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and when you have read them, lay your Hand on your Heart, if it be not hardened, and repent for having revived an old repudiated Doctrine, which will prove Antichriſt to reign by God's Authority, and that he is the Auhor of all Succeſsful Wickedneſſes in the World.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When I firſt began to put Pen to Paper, I did not intend to dwell ſo long upon your Sermon before the Houſe, but there are ſo many looſe paſſages in it, and ſo obnoxious to <hi>ſome among our ſelves,</hi> that I cannot but take notice of them, and ſhew you how they expoſe you for them. In the juſtification of the Prince of <hi>Orange's</hi> Undertaking, you tell us, That <hi>he was no Subject of</hi> England:<note place="margin">P. 19.</note> To which they reply, that you knew this before you took the Oath, and uſed to ſay, that the Prince, though he was not the <hi>King</hi>'s Subject, yet ye was his Enemy, and that we ought to have aided the <hi>King</hi> againſt him as ſuch: And whereas you tell us, that he was an <hi>Independent Prince,</hi> they obſerve, that according to your Principle of Poſſeſſion he was no Prince at all, but that the <hi>French</hi> King had been long Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> by a <hi>Providential Right.</hi> As for what you ſay of his <hi>Relation to the Crown,</hi> and <hi>ſecuring the Succeſſion;</hi> they tell you, to expoſe your weak way of arguing, that <hi>Abſolom</hi> was related to the Crown of <hi>David,</hi> that the Crown hath ſuffered much by its <hi>Relations,</hi> and that the Law is the beſt ſecurity for the Succeſſion. And then as for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> you make upon the <hi>Greateſt Sufferers,</hi> who you tell us <hi>were well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the Prince's undertaking, and could not be perſuaded to declare their Abhorrence of it.</hi> They ſay, if that were true, it did not become you to expoſe them for it, who were greatly offended at the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the Speech which he made to his Highneſs at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and who told a great <hi>Sufferer,</hi> to whom you complained of his Lordſhip, that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of every pleaſing thought you had of the <hi>Prince</hi>'s coming, and beg'd God's pardon that you among the reſt of the Clergy had not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the people to aſſiſt the King againſt him. You alſo went ſo far in oppoſing the <hi>Prince,</hi> as to print an Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Enquiry into the preſent State of Affairs,</hi> which he wrote to facilitate the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Acceſs to the Crown. You alſo wrote an <hi>Apology for the Non-Swearers,</hi> which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66038:8"/> you could not new anſwer, if it were in print; and yet without conſidering that you were one of them, and what <hi>Decorum</hi> you ought, above all others, to keep in ſpeaking of them, you bring this malicious Reflection over again in your firſt Letter concerning the <hi>French Invaſion:</hi> But there will be an Anſwer to it, which will ſufficiently vindicate them, and ſhew what a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophant you are; and therefore I ſhall paſs it over here. In the 20th page you endeavour to excuſe thoſe who were more active in the <hi>Revolution,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly to flatter ſome of the moſt <hi>active Members,</hi> who, you ſay, <hi>At that time while the King continued with us, thought no more than to obtain a free Parliament;</hi> and then you tell us, <hi>That the King would not ſtand Trial, but disbanded his Army, withdrew his Perſon, and leſt no Authority behind him.</hi> To all which, Dr. I muſt beg leave to confront what I find in your Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Enquiry. Sometimes his withdrawing his Perſon and Seals is a giving up the Government,</hi> p. 5. (as if intermiſſion of Government were a total giving up of Right,) <hi>ſo that he cannot claim it again if he returns; and yet he grants the caſe of preſent danger, and juſt fear: This ought not to be preſſed too far; but that it is indecent to ſuppoſe that Kings can be ſubject to fear; that is, we muſt not ſuppoſe them to be Men, for if they are, fear is an humane Paſſion. But he had no juſt cauſe of fear: I will not diſpute that; but ſuppoſe he was affraid without juſt cauſe, Doth not fear ſtill make the Action involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and ſave the forfeiture of the Crown? and if it doth, What difference is there betwixt his firſt and ſecond withdrawing? For it ſeems he apprehends there was more juſt cauſe of fear the ſecond time, and therefore will not lay the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation there, but upon his firſt going; and yet it is a probable Argument, that he was affraid at firſt, becauſe Kings do not uſe to forſake their Kingdoms without Fear. But what need of pretending the King's going away, if the ſubverſion of his Government and Laws diſſolved the Government? For it ſeems he was no King before he went, nor to be looked upon as a King, but a Deſtroyer; ſo that whether he had gone or ſtaid, the thing had been the ſame: But if the King can do no wrong, he can never forfeit his Crown by Male Adminiſtration, at leaſt an</hi> ipſo facto <hi>forfeiture was never heard of in Kings; it is more reaſonable to bring him to a Trial, than to Judge, and Condemn, and Depoſe him without Hearing, which is thought hard uſage for a Subject: But the miſchief is, they know not how to frame the Indictment, where to find Judges, and his Peers to try him; which is an Argument our Law knows nothing of trying Kings, becauſe it hath made no proviſion for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Your obſerving <hi>Readers</hi> laugh at your Confidence, in ſaying,<note place="margin">xxx. p. 22.</note> That the late <hi>Revolution hath made no Alterations in the Principles of Government and Obedience:</hi> And to uſe your own words, <hi>Some</hi> think your Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Right a <hi>tottering Foundation for the Monarchy that cannot long ſupport it,</hi> and every jot as <hi>tottering</hi> as that of the <hi>Power of the People,</hi> which you explode; becauſe the People, if they get the Supream Power of the King, they will plead Providence for it, and keep it, whether they have natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a <hi>Superior Power</hi> over him or no. In page 23. you ſay, <hi>It was a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providence, that the generality of Subjects were meerly Paſſive at the Revolution:</hi> But they ſay, you uſed to bemoan the Paſſiveneſs of them as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66038:9"/> ſinfull, eſpecially in the Clergy; particularly, you were often heard with great formality, to recite ſome words of Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> concerning the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Clergy, which you ſaid, <hi>went like Daggers to your Heart.</hi> It ſeems, once upon a time, you pray'd the Dr. to conſider what a diſhonour the Clergy's taking the Oath would be to our Religion; to which he reply'd, that if that were all, the Honour of our Religion was gone in the ſilence of the Clergy at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Invaſion, though ſome of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy were not ſo ſilent as that Dr. imagined; and when another asked you, how you could forbear at that time to Preach up the Duty of Active Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, as ſome others had done? You anſwered with a ſhew of Tears in your Eyes, that <hi>they were happy Men,</hi> and ſtriking your Hand upon your Breaſt, you wiſhed you had done ſo too. Page 27. You ſay, <hi>There is no appearance of illegal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations, no oppreſſion of the Subjects juſt Rights, nor pretence of Clamour of Perſecution for Conſcience take;</hi> and yet as ſome among us obſerve, according to your own bafled <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of <hi>Right to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> their Majeſties Poſſeſſion of the Throne is not legal, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, how rightful ſoever you pretend to make it in the Eye of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, it is an Uſurpation in the Eye of the Law: And then as for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Conſcience ſake, theſe Men ſay, That of all Men it leaſt became you to aſſert, That there was no pretence to complain of that, who confidently ſaid, <hi>That the late Revolution was the greateſt Scheme of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany that ever was contrived,</hi> and not long ſince had ſuch an high Opinion both of their Conſciences and their Cauſe, and pretended to believe that they were perſecuted not only for Conſcience, but Righteouſneſs ſake. They ſay, they are both the ſame they were as when you were one of them, and though you have changed the Names of them; ſince you chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged your Opinion, yet they think that they ſtill retain their old Nature, and have as much to ſay for themſelves, as you could ſay for them then. Then they ſay, you took it ill to be told by the Writers of the Times, That it was not Conſcience, but Shame, Peeviſhneſs, Stubbornneſs, and other cauſes of prejudice, that made the Non-Swearers ſtand out: And to remove this ſcandalous Imputation from your ſelf and your Brethren, you went on purpoſe to the Excellent Bp. of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> to put him upon making his <hi>Death-Bed Declaration,</hi> at which the Government was ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but ſince you took the Oath, it is no matter of Conſcience, or Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and it is now dwindled into a Gnat, nay into Nothing, which was a Cammel before. Methinks you might remember the great difficulty with which many thouſands that took the Oath took it, and call to mind the lower ſenſe in which they took it, only to live peaceably, and quietly; and how others took it in this ſenſe, only as a Temporary Oath: And if ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mens Conſciences would not let them take it, but in ſuch qualified ſenſes, Why ſhould it not be pure Conſcience in theſe Men to take it in no ſenſe at all? You know the Secret of Dr. <hi>Scot,</hi> why he refuſed the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> it was becauſe his Conſcience would not let him take the Oath of Homage to K. <hi>W.</hi> and Q. <hi>M.</hi> and if that Oath was an inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difficulty to an honeſt and well informed Conſcience in him, Why
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66038:9"/> ſhould not the new Oath of Allegiance be ſo to <hi>theſe Men,</hi> who think thar at leaſt they have a pretence to complain, that they are perſecuted and ſuffe-for Conſcience ſake? They ſay farther, that any Government may perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute by Law, as well as againſt it, and that there is little or no diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence between being oppreſſed and ruined by unjuſt Laws, or unjuſtly againſt Law. Nay, any Perſecution is the greater they ſay, for having Law to ſupport it; and that Conſcience is Conſcience, whether it ſuffer againſt Law by a Tyrant, or by Tyrannical Laws. I remember there is ſomething to this purpoſe ſomewhere in your <hi>Caſe of Reſiſtance;</hi> and then as to the Cauſe for which <hi>theſe Men</hi> ſuffer, no Man, they ſay, had a more full Perſuaſion of the Juſtice of it, than your ſelf. They ſay, you ſcarce had patience to hear your beſt Friends argue againſt it in favour of the Oath; that you told Mr. <hi>Maur,</hi> you <hi>cold as ſoon turn</hi> Arian, <hi>as take it;</hi> and another Gentleman, <hi>That you had conſidered all that had been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or could be ſaid for taking of it; and that you were ſure if you ſhould take it, you ſhould never reſt till you had gone to the ſame place where you took it, and vomit it up again.</hi> You told another, <hi>you thought if you ſhould take it, you ſhould be tempted to deſtroy your ſelf after you took it;</hi> and wondered <hi>that the Government ſhould impoſe an Oath upon Men's Conſciences which would make them hate it for impoſing of it;</hi> nay, ſo confident were you then that you ſuffered for Righteouſneſs, that you took the Courage to tell your Murmuring Wife, <hi>That ſhe would loſe her Reward for Suffering, but you ſhould have yours;</hi> and to another you ſaid with an Accent that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the words upon his Memory, <hi>Our Sufferings, if any thing can, will ſave the Church, and ſtand upon Record for it againſt the Papiſts in times to come, and help to attone the diſpleaſure of God.</hi> Nay, you then thought the Juſtice of your Cauſe ſo plain, and the other ſo indefenſible, that laying one of your Hands upon the other, you ſaid unto a Perſon of Quality, <hi>Theſe Hands ſhould reſtore King</hi> James, <hi>but that my Wife hath tied them up from Writing.</hi> And another of your common ſayings was, <hi>We have a very good Cauſe, but loſe it for want of a Preſs.</hi> A Man famous for ſuch ſayings concerning the Cauſe, when you were a Sufferer for it, ſhould have more Diſcretion, if not more Reſpect for his old Brethren, than to go about to rob them of the Glory of their Sufferings: The Teſtimony of a good Conſcience is all they have left to ſupport them under their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity; and it is very hard to make the World believe they have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to that; and that <hi>there are no Grievances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 23.</note> 
               <hi>unleſs Monarchy and the Church of</hi> England <hi>are remaining Grievances.</hi> This was bravely ſaid by <hi>Ecebolius</hi> for Fifteen Hundred Pounds a Year; but whether there are Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances or no Grievances, Suffering for Conſcience or no ſuch Sufferings, <hi>theſe Men</hi> are perſuaded that it is not only for the <hi>Church,</hi> but for the <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Royal Family</hi> that they ſuffer; and that neither that nor theſe can long ſubſiſt, nor any laſting Peace or true Loyalty be eſtabliſhed among us, but upon the Moral and Political Principles, for which they are perſuaded they witneſs a good Confeſſion before God and Men. As for your Principles, they think them, of all other, the moſt vile and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66038:10"/> ſelfiſh, and to be deteſted of all Sovereign States and Princes, that have any better Title than Poſſeſſion: For your Principles allow Subjects, though tied with never ſo many Oaths, to turn to an Uſurper as faſt as he gains Power, before he is ſettled in the Throne; and after he is ſettled in it, by pure force they oblige them to transfer their whole Allegiance to him; and therefore you deceived her Majeſty, when in the Dedication of your Book of the <hi>Laſt Judgment,</hi> you profeſſed to her with all the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which the Subject requires, <hi>That you were her moſt faithful Subject and Servant:</hi> For a faithful Subject will adhere to his Sovereign in times of Adverſity as well as Proſperity, and ſerve him when he is out, as well as when he is in the Throne, with <hi>Life, Limb, and Terrene Honour:</hi> But your Allegiance by your Principles, is a Flattering, Shifting, and Time-ſerving Allegiance, which you would carry with your Prayers from her Majeſty to her greateſt Enemies, and begin to Flatter, and Serve them from the firſt moment you came under their Power. Such Faithful, and Obedient Subjects as you, are like to Summer Flies; you'll make a great ſhew and buz for your King in fair Weather, when the Sun ſhines, but in Storms and Tempeſts you will hide your Heads; in the long Night-time, or Winter of Adverſity you will ſay, <hi>If he cannot defend himſelf, let him go;</hi> and if he go, as many brave Kings have been forced to do, why then, Doctor, you are not <hi>Men of ſtupid and ſlaviſh Loyalty</hi> to your old Maſter; but like the <hi>Gnat</hi> in the Fable, you'll fly to Court in Swarms, to careſs your new dear Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Maſter, and transfer your Allegiance to him for fear of <hi>being Cruſh'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. From your Sermon before the Houſe I beg leave, good Doctor, to make ſome Reflections upon your <hi>Temple-Church</hi> Sermon, in which, as in your <hi>Faſt-Sermon</hi> before the Queen, you ſpeak the Truth, but not the whole Truth on the Subject of Prayer, eſpecially of publick Prayer, <note n="*" place="margin">P. 8, 9.</note> by the <hi>Biſhop and Miniſters, and whole Congregation.</hi> You tell us, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">P. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Prayers are the moſt Noble Exerciſe of Charity, and that they are moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, becauſe they are offered up in the Spirit of Charity.</hi> And in your <hi>Faſt Sermon</hi> you tell us, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="margin">P. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>Faith and Prayer are more powerful than Arms, and that fervent and importunate Prayers are the moſt ſure way to Conquer our Enemies, and to prevail with God for a Bleſſing upon our Arms.</hi> Now, Doctor, all this, as <hi>Some</hi> obſerve, was ſaid a thouſand times in the great Rebellion, when the Preachers of the Times made God a Party to their Wickedneſs, and aſcribed all their Succeſs to <hi>Prayer.</hi> They cited <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>Barach,</hi> and <hi>Samſon,</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> as you <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>f ſ</hi> p. 26, 27.</note> do: But then after the Reſtauration, our Church Divines uſed to obſerve, that <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as well as <hi>Charity,</hi> was neceſſary to make <hi>Prayers</hi> acceptable to God, and that the Fanatick Preachers, though they talked ſo much of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and of Faith, and Charity, and Fervency in Prayer, and produced the Worthies of Scripture for Examples to ſhew the power of <hi>Prayer;</hi> yet they never ſaid one word of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> without which <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Prayer</hi> is but a falſe Enthuſiaſtical Perſuaſion, Fervency Enthuſiaſtical Heat, all pretences to <hi>Charity Hypocriſie:</hi> And <hi>Prayers</hi> themſelves, tho' never ſo frequent, or long, but an Abomination to the Lord. Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66038:10"/> is very large on this Subject in his <hi>Jewiſh Hypocriſie,</hi> which I commend to all Men's reading for his ſake. In that Diſcourſe he ſhews at large how the Spirit of <hi>Phariſaiſme</hi> was long regnant in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, before the time of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and that it conſiſted in a <hi>Great,</hi> but <hi>Hypocritical</hi> Zeal for <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Praying,</hi> and all Religious Duties; and under that Cloak to commit Injuſtice, Rapine, and Oppreſſion, as our Lord obſerved of the <hi>Phariſees, That they devoured Widows Houſes,</hi> and for a pretence <hi>made long Prayers.</hi> To this purpoſe our Clergy uſed generally to preach on <hi>Publick Faſts</hi> and <hi>Thankſgivings;</hi> and truly there is ſo much <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> regnant in the World, that they did well in doing ſo; but now of late, as if <hi>Aſtraea</hi> were returned from Heaven, and the <hi>Golden Age</hi> reſtored, we have either nothing, or very little ſaid of <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon <hi>Publick Faſts</hi> and <hi>Thanksgivings;</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> the moſt Difficult as well as Divine Virtue, without which there is no <hi>Charity,</hi> nor no acceptance of <hi>Prayers,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for Kings and Kingdoms at the Throne of Grace. You tell us in your <hi>Faſt Sermon, That God never delivered the</hi> Jews <hi>into the Hands of their Enemies, but when they were guilty of Idolatry:</hi> But if you read the <hi>Jewiſh Hypocriſie,</hi> you will find that <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> as well as <hi>Idolatry,</hi> was a ſocial cauſe of God's Judgments, and that their Prophets thundered againſt that, as much as againſt this. I am very ſenſible, Doctor, that there is not ſo much <hi>Idolatry</hi> among us, as there was among the <hi>Jews;</hi> but as for <hi>Injuſtice</hi> in all its kinds and degrees, it is a reigning ſin among us, and calls for plain and home Reproofs from the Pulpit, as much as any other ſin. <hi>Cry aloud and ſpare not,</hi> is now as much as ever the incumbent Duty of the Clergy. They ought in their Solemn Meetings more eſpecially to tell the People of their Sin, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of their Tranſgreſſions, becauſe they have filled the Land with Violence, as the Prophet ſpeaks, their Maſters Houſe with Violence and Deceit. Our <hi>Faſts</hi> and <hi>Thanksgivings,</hi> Doctor, will ſtand us in no ſtead, 'till we begin our Reformation here. You know what is written, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 1. better than I do: O, Doctor, let the Prophet there become your Example on the Solemn Aſſemblies! You uſed to value your ſelf for your ſingular boldneſs in rebuking Vice, and now is the time to exerciſe that Talent, now is the needful time to preach up <hi>Juſtice, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> without reſpect of perſons; to ſet your Face like Flint againſt our Jewiſh Chriſtians, and tell them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on our <hi>Faſts</hi> and <hi>Thanksgivings,</hi> that the beſt way of <hi>Praying,</hi> is to looſe the bands of Wickedneſs, and to let the Oppreſſed go free. Oh that you had the Spirit and Tongue of St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> or the Spirit of <hi>Hugh Latimer,</hi> though without <hi>John</hi>'s Eloquence, to tell them plainly what is Right and Wrong; to tell them as plainly as Tongue is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it; as plainly as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> told <hi>Herod,</hi> and in the hearing of the <hi>Herodians, That it was not lawfull for him to have his Brother</hi> Philip's <hi>Wife.</hi> Oh, Doctor, when I can hear you preach with this freedom, againſt the <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> of the Times, as <hi>John</hi> did againſt <hi>Herod,</hi> or our Saviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> among whom there were ſo many <hi>Herodians;</hi> then I will have as high an Opinion of the <hi>Prayers</hi> of Biſhops and Prieſts, as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66038:11"/> you can deſire, and think that they will prevail for a Bleſſing upon our Arms; but till I can hear them preach at this rate, or ſomething near it, I ſhall be apt to fear that the God of Righteouſneſs will have no delight in their <hi>Prayers,</hi> becauſe his Eyes are over the Righteous, and his Ears are open to their <hi>Prayers,</hi> Lyars and Robbers, and Thieves, and Oppreſſors, how Great and Sanctimonious ſoever, may pray unto God, and the moſt cunning of them, like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> may be more Zealous for Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and make a better Figure than their Neighbours in the Houſe of <hi>Prayer;</hi> but their moſt ſplendid Sacrifices are but Dogs fleſh: The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God, though he has the patience to hear them, he abhors them, and returns their moſt fervent <hi>Prayers</hi> changed into <hi>Curſes</hi> upon their own Heads. Nay, Sir, the moſt righteous perſons, in your Language, the <hi>Patron Saints and Tutelar Angels of the World,</hi> though they pray with never ſo much Faith and Fervency, and in never ſo large and extenſive Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; yet they pray to no purpoſe, when by miſtake they pray for the ſucceſs of an unjuſt Cauſe or Undertaking, believing of it to be juſt. In ſuch a Caſe the Righteous God, though he may accept their good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and reward their Faith and Charity; yet he will not hear their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken <hi>Prayers.</hi> It is againſt his Eſſential Juſtice which is one of his Moral Attributes, to hear Unrighteous and Immoral <hi>Prayers.</hi> He may indeed order Events according to good Men's Unrighteous Deſires, but that is for Wiſe Reaſons of his own, and not upon the account of their Deſires, as now in <hi>Flanders</hi> he hath, giving the <hi>French</hi> King ſuch amazing Succeſſes; but if he be ſuch a Tyrant as you deſcribe him to be, then his Succeſſes are not to be aſcribed to his good Subjects <hi>Prayers,</hi> but to the ſecret Reaſons of Divine Wiſdom, which time will Repeal. So the <hi>Herodians,</hi> as <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pray'd for the Proſperity of</hi> Herod, <hi>and kept his Birth-Day:</hi> But, Doctor, neither you nor I believe, that the Tyrant throve ever the better for a pack of ſneaking <hi>Court-Rabbies:</hi> And ſo <hi>Some</hi> alive, in great Places, pray'd for the Proſperity of <hi>Cromwel;</hi> but it is not reaſonable to believe, that God placed that Villain in the Throne, or kept him five years in it, at the inſtance of their unrighteous <hi>Prayers,</hi> but to make him a ſcourge to the Nation for our Sins.</p>
            <p n="10">10. I now paſs with you from your general Diſcourſe of <hi>Prayer</hi> to your particular Directions of <hi>praying for Kings,</hi> where, to your coſt, you have fallen upon <hi>Some among our Selves,</hi> for aſſerting, that by Kings the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle meant only lawfull and rightfull Kings; and directs only to pray for Kings that have the Legal Right. In your <hi>Faſt Sermon,</hi> you call them <note n="*" place="margin">P. 19</note> 
               <hi>Deluded Proteſtants;</hi> and it is a favour you will allow them to be <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants:</hi> For one of the irregular Biſhops lately told his Clergy, <hi>That they were acted by the Jeſuits;</hi> but in this you point at them by the gentle <hi>Innuendo</hi> of <hi>Some,</hi> and <hi>theſe Men. Some</hi> ſuch indeed there are among us, whom in your firſt Letter concerning the <hi>French Invaſion,</hi> you tax of <hi>Stupid and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Some</hi> of <hi>theſe Men</hi> have baffled you, as much as ever Man was baffled, and made your Friends bluſh for you; and wiſh (as I believe you your ſelf have often done) that you had never medled with the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66038:11"/> But, Sir, Though you are pleaſed to call them Men, (yet in effect) you make them <hi>Monſters,</hi> and <hi>Mad-Men,</hi> whoſe <note n="*" place="margin">P. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Reaſonings contradict the general Senſe, and Practice of Mankind in all Revolutions;</hi> and boldly aſſert with an Air of Confidence peculiar to Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">P. 20.</note> That the <hi>Generality of Mankind, and even the moſt Sober and Conſidering Men reject them, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no ſolid Foundation in Reaſon and Nature.</hi> Whether that be ſo or no, we ſhall ſee anon; but at preſent let us enquire whether their Opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the general ſenſe and practice of Mankind, and even of the moſt ſober and conſidering Men; if it do, the general conſent of Mankind, or of the moſt ſober and conſidering Men, is a great preſumption againſt them; but if it do not, then give me leave to tell you, that you are not a <hi>Man of Stupid and Slaviſh, Modeſty,</hi> but that your Impudence is a Scandal to the Pulpit, and that you have juſtly provoked the <hi>Templers</hi> to ſay of you, as a Gentleman ſaid to one of your Sworn Brethren, that they will never again believe a <hi>Parſon</hi> for your ſake. One of your learned Antagoniſts hath obſerved, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>b.</hi> p. 48.</note> That you acknowledge St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to be of their Opinion, and he hath cited St. <hi>Baſil</hi> againſt you for ſaying ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>That the Higher Powers mention'd by the Apoſtle, were ſuch as attain to the Government by Humane Laws.</hi> I hope, Doctor, you will grant, that theſe two Fathers were ſober, and conſidering Men, who underſtood the general ſenſe of Mankind; and according to this ſenſe, in which they underſtood the Apoſtle, that Author goes on to ſhew that it was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of the Primitive Chriſtians to ſide with that Emperor who had the Legal Title: And to their practice I will add the Teſtimony of the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> in his Letters to <note n="*" place="margin">Procop. Caeſ. <hi>de Bello Vanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico,</hi> l. 1. c. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Gelimer,</hi> King <hi>de Facto</hi> of the Kingdom of the <hi>Vandals</hi> in <hi>Affrica,</hi> who depoſed his Couſin <hi>Hildericus,</hi> between whom and <hi>Juſtinian</hi> there was always great Friendſhip: But to make you underſtand the Emperor's Letter to this Uſurper the better, I muſt acquaint you, Doctor, that <hi>Gizericus,</hi> the Founder of that Monarchy, who reigned Thirty Nine years, ſettled the Succeſſion in his Poſterity upon the Male Deſcendents according to Seniority; ſo that he ſhould always come to the Crown, who was the Eldeſt among them; and accordingly the Crown had peaceably deſcended for four Succeſſions to <hi>Hildericus,</hi> whom <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limer</hi> depos'd, and ſhut up in Priſon with his Brother's two Sons, who were faithful to their Uncle. As ſoon as <hi>Juſtinian</hi> heard of it, he wrote to him to this effect; <q>Thou haſt acted, <hi>Gelimer,</hi> againſt Right and Duty, and contrary to the Teſtament of <hi>Gizericus,</hi> in Impriſoning an Old Man, and thy Kinſman, and the King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> if the Eſtabliſhment of <hi>Gizericus</hi> be valid, and depoſing him by force from the Government, to which thou mighteſt have lawfully ſucceeded. Do not perſit in thy Wickedneſs, nor prefer the Name of a Tyrant before the Title of a King, which a little time would give thee; but let the Old Man, who cannot live long, enjoy the Royal Power and Dignity, and do thou Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter under him, and be content to wait a little while, till thou mayeſt take upon thee the Title of King, acording to the Law of <hi>Gize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi> by doing this thou wilt pleaſe God, and oblige me.</q> This Letter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66038:12"/> having no effect upon the Uſurper, he wrote again to this purpoſe. <q>I wrote my former Letter to thee, hoping thou wouldſt not perſiſt to act contrary to my Advice; but ſince thou art reſolved to keep Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, as thou haſt acquired it, take what will follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; only ſend unto us <hi>Hildericus,</hi> and <hi>Hoemer,</hi> whoſe Eyes thou haſt put out, with his Brother <hi>Evagees,</hi> that they may receive ſuch Conſolation from us, the one for the loſs of his Kingdom, and the other for the loſs of his ſight, as Men in their Condition are capable of. It is in your power to do this, if you do it quickly; otherwiſe the confidence they have in Us, will oblige Us ſpeedily to help them; nor will it be any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraction of the Peace which our Predeceſſors made with <hi>Gizericus,</hi> for I ſhall not make War with one that is his Succeſſor, but avenge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries thou haſt done.</q> But <hi>Gelimer</hi> was too Ambitious to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and therefore <hi>Justinian</hi> ſent his great General <hi>Balſarius</hi> to make War upon him in behalf of <hi>Hildericus,</hi> the lawfull King; but the firſt thing that <hi>Gelimer</hi> did after the Landing of <hi>Beliſarius,</hi> was to Murder <hi>Hilderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus;</hi> but God avenged his blood upon the Uſurper, whom <hi>Beliſarius</hi> after ſome years War brought Captive to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where he cried out on the way as he was led to the Emperor, <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Teſtimony of a Chriſtian Emperor, I ſhall add another of a famous Heathen Prince, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> who though he came lawfully to the Poſſeſſion of the Crown, yet refuſed to keep it longer than he was allow'd by Law, as appears by the following Story, which you may find in his Life written by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the following words. <q>This Confuſion and Diſorder continued a long time in <hi>Sparta,</hi> which occaſion'd the death of the King the Father of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> for as he was endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to quell a Riot, in which the Parties were a fighting, he was ſtab'd with a Cook's Knife, and left the Kingdom to his Eldeſt Son <hi>Polydectes;</hi> but he too dying ſoon after, the Right of Succeſſion, as all Men judged, reſted in <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> and he Reigned untill it was perceived, that the Queen his Siſter in Law was with Child: But as ſoon as this appear'd, he declared, that the Kingdom belonged to her Iſſue, if it proved a Male, and that he would adminiſter the Government only as his Guardian and Regent. Soon after a private offer was made him by the Queen, that ſhe would make her ſelf miſcarry, upon condition he would Marry her, when he was ſure of the Crown. He hated the Woman for this wicked Propoſal, yet wiſely ſmothering his reſentment, he did not ſpeak aſtainſt it, but ſeem'd to approve and accept it; but diſwaded her ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly from making her ſelf miſcarry, becauſe it might endanger her Health, or her Life; aſsuring her, that himſelf would take care that the Child, as ſoon as it was born, ſhould be taken out of the way. Thus having drawn on the Queen to the time of her Labour, as ſoon as he heard ſhe was in Travail, he ſent ſome to be preſent and obſerve the Birth, with order that if it were a Girl, they ſhould deliver it to the Women, but if a Boy, they ſhould bring it to him, whatſoever he he happened to be a doing. It happened that the Queen was delivered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66038:12"/> of a Boy while he was at Supper with the principal Magiſtrates, and his Servants brought the Boy to him as he was at Table; and he taking him into his Arms, ſaid to thoſe about him, <hi>Behold, my Lords of</hi> Sparta, <hi>here is your King;</hi> and having ſaid this, he laid him down upon the Chair of State, and named him <hi>Charilaus;</hi> that is, <hi>The Joy of the People,</hi> becauſe they were ſo much tranſported with Joy at the Birth of the young Prince, and with Admiration at the Noble Mind and Juſtice of <hi>Lycurgus;</hi> who I fear, Doctor, will riſe up in Judgment againſt you, and condemn you and your unrighteous Doctrine:</q> For though he had Providence on his ſide, as much as ever Prince had; yet he did not think the Providence of the Gods could give him a Right againſt the Laws of Nature and <hi>Sparta:</hi> And therefore he became a Subject of a Sovereign, and of a King a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; becauſe he could not juſtly wear a Crown, which by the Law of his Countrey became another's, and ceaſed to be his. And to paſs over other Kingdoms, I will proceed to ſhew that there have been many Wiſe and Brave Men of that Opinion in our own: I will begin with the Reign of <hi>Stephen,</hi> who as <hi>Hoveden</hi> ſaith, <hi>Invaded the Crown of</hi> England <hi>like a Tempeſt, ſo that all the Nation was forced to ſubmit to him, as it were in the twinkling of an Eye.</hi> He was, Doctor, as you ſpeak, Recogniz'd for King by the States of the Realm, and the great Body of the Nation ſubmitted to him, and took the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> to him, who himſelf had taken that Oath to Queen <hi>Maud,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> her Son; and yet though he had all the <hi>Enſigns</hi> of <hi>Majeſty</hi> by Coronation, and was in full Poſſeſſion of the Throne, which you call a <hi>thorough Settlement;</hi> there were many Gallant Men, who would not acquieſs in the Publick Judgment of the Nation, becauſe it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent, and erroneous, but after ſome time oppoſed him to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as an Uſurper, although he had Providence on his ſide. Among theſe was <note n="*" place="margin">Dicerem, niſi adulatio videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non imparem fuiſſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Julio Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari. Robertus</hi> Chriſtiana Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate inſignis. Anno <hi>1139.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Robert,</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> half Brother to Queen <hi>Maud,</hi> who (as <hi>Malmsbury</hi> ſaith) was the moſt Learned, Pious, and Valiant Man of his Age. Indeed <hi>Robert</hi> with a relucting Conſcience, had done Homage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally to <hi>Stephen,</hi> but though he did it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, he ſoon recovered himſelf, and repented of it and took care <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Robertus</hi> quaſi poſitus in ſpeculâ Rerum providebat exitum, &amp; ne de juramento quod fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerat ſorori erga Deum &amp; Homines <hi>perfidiae</hi> notaretur ſedulo cagitabat. <hi>Anno 1137.</hi>
               </note> to act nothing contrary to his Allegiance to <hi>Maud;</hi> and with the firſt ſafe opportunity <note n="†" place="margin">Homagio etiam abdicato rationem praeſerens, quàm injuſte id fecerat, quia &amp; Rex <hi>illicite</hi> ad Regnum aſpiraverat. — Ipſemet etiam <hi>contra Legem</hi> egeciſſet, qui poſt Sacramentum quod ſorori dedirat, alteri cuilibet, ea viven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, ſe manus dare non trubuiſſet.</note> ſent Meſſengers to <hi>Stephen</hi> to tell him, <hi>That he renounced his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigteous Oath of Homage to him, and that he had acted contrary to Law, in that he was not aſhamed to Swear Homage to any Mortal while his Siſter was alive.</hi> And afterwards, as I ſhall ſhew, he could never be brought to turn Subject to <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> in the greateſt extremity, when they threatned to take away his Life if he would not. The Hiſtorians, who I believe were ſober Men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent <hi>Stephen</hi> as a <note n="‡" place="margin">Quamvis ipſe juraſſet juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fidelitatis Imperatrici, &amp; <hi>Henrico</hi> filio ſuo, tamen quaſi Tempeſtas invaſit Diadema Regni <hi>Angliae.</hi> Qui ſi legitime Regnum fuiſſet ingreſſus— <hi>Hoveden.</hi> Qui Rex illicite ad Regnum aſpicaverat,— <hi>Malmsbury.</hi> Sed dum externam vim propulſat, Domeſtica petitur, jam manifeſte Deo Perjurii poenas ob eo expectente. <hi>Polyd. Virg.</hi>
               </note> Perjured Uſurper, and complain of the Perjury of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66038:13"/> the Times, and ſay, that it brought down the Judgment of God upon the Land, <note n="‖" place="margin">Quibus, De propitio, ſalubriter actis Rex <hi>Angliam</hi> &amp; <hi>Angliae</hi> Pacem recepit, Annis enim jam plarimis ſere nudo Regis nomine inſignis tunc recipere vijus eſt hujus rem nominis, quia tunc primo, purgata invaſionis Tyrannica Macula Legitimi Principis Juſtitiam inducit.</note> 
               <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigenſis</hi> ſaith, that he was but a <hi>Nominal</hi> King till the Pacification or Agreement made with <hi>Henry,</hi> and that it was that which made him a <hi>Real, Lawfull,</hi> and <hi>Rightful</hi> King. Nay, the Hiſtorians obſerve in what a ſignal manner the Judgment of God fell upon the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who were the two firſt that ſwore Allegiance to him, the former not ſurviving a year to an end, and the latter being made a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by him, was miſerably vexed by him till he died of Grief. <hi>Malmsbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> tells us, <hi>That God made him an example to Men, not to truſt in uncertain Riches, which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Some Men coveting after, concerning Faith have made Shipwreck.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1138.</note> He alſo tells us, that <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> conſulted many Religious Men, to know their Opinion, if he might quit his Allegiance to his Siſter: And that they anſwered, <hi>He could neither live in this World with Honour, nor in Everlaſting Happineſs in the World to come, if he acted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Oath which he had taken to her.</hi> I ſuppoſe, Doctor, the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men, whom that Learned and Wiſe Prince conſulted, as the Guides of his Conſcience, were as good Men and Caſuiſts as that Age afforded; and they being dead, yet ſpeak, and give Evidence againſt you, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting that the Opinion and Reaſonings of <hi>Some among our ſelves,</hi> is againſt the general ſenſe of Mankind. If Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> in his <hi>Church Hiſtory</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the mater right, all the Arguments which you and your Brethren uſed for taking the new Oath of Allegiance, were then uſed to juſtifie Swearing Allegiance to <hi>Stephen,</hi> but Earl <hi>Robert,</hi> to uſe your words, felt not the force of them, he had nothing left him but a <hi>Stupid and Slaviſh Allegiance</hi> to <hi>Maud;</hi> for when he was promiſed to be made as great as <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> the Throne only excepted, if he would become his Subject; he <hi>made this Anſwer, which</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno 1143.</hi> Non ſum mei (inquit) ſed alleni juris—</note> ſaith the Hiſtorian) <hi>I deſire Poſterity may know and admire; I am not at my own diſpoſal, but under the Right of another; but when I ſhall have power over my ſelf, I ſhall do what the reaſon of the Caſe ſhall direct.</hi> After this Anſwer, Doctor, which he made in defence of his Allegiance to a Queen that never was Crown'd; the Lords, who brought the Meſſage from <hi>Stephen</hi> to him, began to threaten him with Impriſonment and Death: And what reply do you think he made to that? Why, <hi>Slave of Allegiance</hi> as he was to <hi>Maud,</hi> he told them with a ſerene Countenance, <hi>That he feared nothing leſs.</hi> After this, again <hi>Stephen</hi> with the Great Lords came in Perſon to him, but he <note n="*" place="margin">Ille velut Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagi rupes immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</note> 
               <hi>ſtood like a Rock againſt the Waves,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting to them, that he had eſpouſed his Siſters Cauſe, neither out of the proſpect of any Worldly advantage, nor <hi>out of hatred to the King,</hi> but purely out of Conſcience, in conſideration of his Duty and Oath, which the Pope had aſſured him did tie him to her <hi>Obedience.</hi> Thus, Doctor, we ſee, that God in the moſt corrupt times, reſerves ſome to bear witneſs to Truth, as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Except the Lord of Hoſts had left us a very ſmall remnant, we ſhould have been as</hi> Sodom, <hi>and like unto</hi> Gomorrah.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66038:13"/> The unnatural Uſurpation of <hi>Edward</hi> III. was ſo ſhort before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's death, that there was not time enough for thoſe who abhorred it to ſignalize their deteſtation of it. But however, Doctor, there were <note n="*" place="margin">Non deerant qui ejus vicem dolentes ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Principes perfidiae, ac <hi>Edoardum</hi> Regem ac <hi>Iſabellam</hi> impietatis criminis notarent— Aliqui Optimates, Auctore <hi>Edmundo</hi> Cantii Comite, ſecreta paſſim jam conſilia &amp; Sermones delibera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndo <hi>Edoardo</hi> una conſerre ceperunt. <hi>Polyd. Virg. Ang.</hi> Hiſt. lib. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Some</hi> who lamented the injuries that <hi>Edward</hi> II. had ſuffered, and were not affraid openly to reproach his Queen and Son of Impiety and Injuſtice. <hi>Edmund</hi> the Great Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> with ſome other perſons, began to Conſpire againſt them: Which Q. <hi>Iſabel,</hi> (who deſerves the name of <hi>Jeſabel</hi>) perceiving, privately encouraged the Keepers of her Husband to murder him, but his Son coming to Maturity of Underſtanding, avenged his blood on <hi>Mortimer,</hi> his Mother's Minion, and his Accomplices, whom the Lords of Parliament, with his aſſent, adjudged and condemned to be executed as Traitors, for murdering the King after he was depoſed. The Queen her ſelf alſo had like to have been queſtioned, and in the Roll 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> III. which gives an account of this matter, he is ſtiled by all the Lords, and the young King himſelf, <hi>their King and Leige Lord.</hi> And in the 21 <hi>R.</hi> II. <hi>N.</hi> 64, 65. the Revocation of the Act for the two <hi>Spencers</hi> Reſtitution in the Parliament of 1 <hi>Edward</hi> III. was repealed, becauſe made at ſuch a time by King <hi>Edw.</hi> III. as his Father, being <hi>very King,</hi> was Living and Impriſoned. Theſe two Acts of Parliament, Doctor, do not at all agree with your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings for the Providential King; but they agree moſt exactly with the Reaſonings of <hi>Some Men,</hi> which you ſay, <hi>contradicts the general ſenſe of Mankind.</hi> For as Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> well obſerves, they ſhew that <hi>Edw.</hi> II. was King <hi>de jure,</hi> or King in the Eye of the Law, as much after his Depoſition as before it; and by conſequence that his Depoſition by the Eſtates, who had no Authority to Depoſe him, was a void Act; and if he was very King when he was in Priſon, and his Regnant Son's King, and Leige Lord at the time of his murder, as the aforeſaid Acts declare him; then, Doctor, I fear it will follow that a pure Providential K. in Poſſeſſion, is no King at all.</p>
            <p n="11">11. But from this Uſurpation let us paſs to that of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. who was ſet up by Providence, and the Eſtates of the Realm, who took upon them to depoſe <hi>Richard</hi> II. and place <hi>Henry</hi> in his Throne. But <hi>Henry</hi> being conſcious to himſelf that he wanted Legal Right, though he had all the Right that Providence could give him; yet not daring to truſt to ſuch an airy Tite, nor his falſe pretences of being the right Heir, cauſed <hi>Richard</hi> to be murdered; but between his Depoſition and Murder, <hi>Thomas Merks</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> a Brave and Godly Prelate, preferring his Duty before his Safety, took the courage to make a Speech in Parliament, againſt the Validity of <hi>Richard</hi>'s Depoſition, and the Juſtice of <hi>Henry</hi>'s Election; and if you pleaſe, Doctor, to read this Speech as it is at large in our Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, you will find, in ſpight of all your prejudice, that he was a very <hi>Wiſe and Conſidering Man,</hi> and entirely of <hi>theſe Mens</hi> Opinion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced thoſe Reaſons for it which you ſay, <hi>Contradict the general ſenſe of Mankind in all Revolutions.</hi> The firſt part of his Speech is to prove, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66038:14"/> a King may not be depoſed by his Subjects for any imputation of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Tyranny; and to make this out clearly, he brings an ugly Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary diſtinction betwixt Kings in a <hi>Popular</hi> or <hi>Conſular</hi> State, which really have not Regal Rights, but are ſubject to a Superior Power; and Kings in whom the Sovereign Majeſty is, as it formerly was in the Kingdoms of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> &amp;c. and now is in the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Spain, France,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. in which the Sovereignty, or Supream Authority is in the King. After this diſtinction (which <hi>Some among us</hi> now uſe) he aſſerts, that in ſuch Kingdoms where the Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is by Law in the King, although the Prince for his Vices be unprofitable to his Subjects, yea hurtfull, yea intollerable; yet they cannot law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully harm his Perſon, or hazard his Power by Judgment, or by Force; becauſe neither one, nor all the Magiſtrates have any Authority over him from whom all Authority is deriv'd, and whoſe only preſence doth ſilence and ſuſpend all inferior Juriſdictions and Power; and as for force, ſaith he, what Subject can attempt, aſſiſt, or counſel, or conceal Violence againſt his Prince, and not incurr the high and heinous Crime of Treaſon? Then he proceeds to prove this as you do in your <hi>Caſe of Non-reſiſtance,</hi> from Examples of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahab,</hi> in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and many Texts of Scripture. Then he proceeds to anſwer the great Objection thus: <hi>Doth the King enjoyn Actions contrary to the Law of God? We muſt neither wholly Obey, nor violently Reſiſt, but with a conſtant courage ſubmit our ſelves to all manner of Puniſhment, and ſhew our ſubjection by enduring, and not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.— Oh how ſhall the World be peſtered with Tyrants, if Subjects may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel upon every pretence of Tyranny? How many good Princes may be ſuppreſſed by thoſe by whom they ought to be ſupported? If they Levy a Subſidy or other Taxation, it ſhall be claimed Oppreſſion; if they put any to Death for Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous attempts againſt their Perſons, it ſhall be exclaimed Cruelty; if they do any thing againſt the luſt and liking of the People, it ſhall be proclaimed Tyranny.</hi> Having ſhew'd, as his words are, that King <hi>Richard</hi> was depoſed <hi>without Authority:</hi> Then he proceeds to ſhew that <hi>Henry</hi> had no Title. Firſt, Not as Heir to <hi>Richard,</hi> which he pretended; for then he ought to ſtay till King <hi>Richard</hi> was dead; but then if K. <hi>Richard</hi> was dead, it was well known there were Deſcendents from <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> whoſe Offspring had been declared in the High Court of Parliament, next Succeſſor to the Crown, in caſe K. <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould die without Iſſue. Secondly, Not by Conqueſt, becauſe a Subject can have no right of Conqueſt againſt a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, where the War is Rebellion, and the Victory High Treaſon. Nor thirdly, by K. <hi>Richard</hi>'s <hi>Reſignation,</hi> becauſe he made it in Priſon where it was exacted of him by force; and therefore it had no force or validity to bind him. Nor laſt of all, by Election, for (ſaith he) we have no Cuſtom that the People at pleaſure ſhould Elect their King, but they <hi>are always bound unto him, who by Right of Blood is Rightfull Succeſſor;</hi> much leſs can they make good or confirm that Title which is before Uſurped by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Then he ſaith, that the depoſing of <hi>Edw.</hi> II. (which the Barons produced for an Example to depoſe <hi>Richard</hi>) was no more to be urged,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66038:14"/> than the Poiſoning of K. <hi>John,</hi> or the Murdering any other lawful Prince, and that we muſt live <hi>according to Laws, and not according to Example,</hi> and that the Kingdom however then was not taken from the lawfull Succeſſor. Then after ſaying many other things, he concludes thus; <hi>I have declared my mind concerning this Queſtion in more words than your Wiſdom, yet fewer than the weight of the Cauſe requires; and boldly conclude, that we have neither Power nor Policy either to depoſe King</hi> Richard, <hi>or to Elect Duke</hi> Henry <hi>into his Place; and that</hi> K. <hi>Richard</hi> ſtill remaineth our Sovereign Prince, <hi>and that it is not lawfull for us to give Judgment upon him; and that the Duke, whom you call King, hath more offended againſt the King and the Realm, than the King hath done againſt him or us.</hi> Thus, Sir, ſpoke that Heroick Prelate in the Court of Parliament, and his practice was anſwerable to what he ſpoke: For he <hi>choſe not the ſafer, but the juſter ſide,</hi> as all good Men ought to do. He knew while he ſpoke, that Bonds and Perſecutions would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him; nevertheleſs he ſpoke freely, and after ſpeaking, was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Priſon, and after that was <hi>cruſhed</hi> with many other brave Men, by the Uſurper againſt whom they roſe up. Afterwards about the ſixth year of his Reign, <hi>Rich. Scroop</hi> A. B. of <hi>York,</hi> with the L. <hi>Maubray</hi> Marſhal of <hi>England, H. Piercy</hi> E. of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> L. <hi>Bardolf,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">As I ſuppoſe, the Earls of <hi>Salisbury, Huntington, Gloceſter,</hi> the Lords <hi>Clarenden, Roper,</hi> with divers other Knights and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquires; and after that the Lord <hi>Thomas Piercy</hi> Earl of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Lord <hi>Henry Piercy,</hi> Son and Heir to the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland.</hi>
               </note> many others, publiſhed an Excommunication and <note n="†" place="margin">In the firſt Volume of <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Acts and Monuments</hi> in the Reign of <hi>H.</hi> IV.</note> Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, conſiſting of ſeveral Articles, againſt <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which they fixed upon the doors of Churches and Monaſteries to be read of all. It begins thus:</p>
            <p>IN THE NAME OF GOD, <hi>Amen. Before the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Judge of the quick and the dead; We not long ſince became bound by Oath upon the Sacred Evangelical Book unto our Sovereign Lord</hi> Richard, <hi>late King of</hi> England, <hi>that we</hi> as long as we lived <hi>ſhould bear true Allegiance, and Fidelity towards him, and his Heirs ſucceeding him in the Kingdom by</hi> juſt Title, Right, and Line according to the Statutes and cuſtom of this Realm; <hi>have here taken unto us certain Articles ſubſcribed in form following, to be proponed, heard, and tried before the</hi> juſt Judge, Chriſt Jeſus, and the whole World; <hi>but if (which God forbid) by Force, Fear, or Violence of wicked Perſons, we ſhall be caſt in Priſon, or by violent death be prevented, ſo as in this World we ſhall not be able to prove the ſaid Articles as we wiſh, then we do</hi> appeal to the High Coeleſtial Judge, <hi>that he may judge and diſcern the ſame in the day of his Supream Judgment. Firſt, We depoſe, ſay, and except, and intend to prove againſt Lord</hi> Henry Darby, commonly called King of <hi>England,</hi> (himſelf pretending the ſame, but without all Right and Title thereunto) <hi>and againſt his Adherents, Fautors, Complices, that they have ever been, are, and will be Traitors, Invaders, and deſtroyers of God's Church, and of our Sovereign Lord</hi> Richard, <hi>late King of</hi> England, <hi>his Heirs, his Kingdom, and Commonwealth, as ſhall hereafter manifeſtly appear.</hi>— In the ſecond Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle they declare him forſworn, perjured, and excommunicate, for that he conſpired againſt his Sovereign Lord King <hi>Richard.</hi> In the fourth they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66038:15"/> recite by what wrong, illegal, and falſe means he exalted himſelf into the Throne of the Kingdom; and then deſcribing the miſerable State of the Nation, which followed after his Uſurpation, they again pronounce him Perjured and Excommunicate. In the fifth Article they ſet forth in what a barbarous and inhumane manner <hi>Henry</hi> and his Accomplices impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and murdered K. <hi>Richard,</hi> and then cry out, Wherefore O <hi>England</hi> ariſe, ſtand up, and avenge the Cauſe, the Death and Injury of thy King and Prince; if thou do not, take this for certain, that the Righteous God will deſtroy thee by ſtrange Invaſions, and Forreign Power, and avenge himſelf on thee for this ſo horrible an Act. In the ſeventh they depoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for putting to death not only Lords Spiritual, and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Men, but alſo divers of the Lords Temporal there Named; for which they pronounce him Excommunicate. In the ninth they ſay, and depoſe, that the Realm of <hi>England</hi> never flouriſhed nor proſpered after he Tyrannically took upon him the Government of it. And in the laſt they depoſe and proteſt for themſelves, and K. <hi>Richard</hi> and his Heirs, the Clergy, Commonwealth of the whole Realm, that they intended neither in Word nor Deed, to offend any State of Men in the Realm, but to prevent the approaching Deſtruction of it, and beſeeching all Men to favour them and their Deſigns, whereof the firſt was, <hi>to exalt to the Kingdom the true and lawfull Heir, and him to Crown in Kingly Throne with the Diadem of England.</hi> Upon publiſhing theſe Articles, much people reſorted to the Archbiſhop, but he being circumvented by the Earl of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> who pretended to join with him, diſmiſſed his Forces at his perſuaſion, upon which he was immediately made Priſoner, and beheaded at <hi>York,</hi> with the Earl Marſhal, and divers <hi>York ſhire</hi> Gentlemen and Citizens of <hi>York,</hi> who had joined with him. The Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and Lord <hi>Bardolph</hi> eſcaped, and held out two years longer before they were cruſhed by the Uſurper; but at laſt they were both ſlain Fighting in the Field againſt him. You ſee, Doctor, in this Remonſtrance how the Archbiſhop, and Lords that joined with him, contrary to the <hi>general ſenſe of Mankind,</hi> unking'd this <hi>Providential King</hi> for want of a <hi>Legal Title,</hi> and Remonſtrated againſt him as a <hi>Perjured Traytor</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper;</hi> and when he lay upon his Death-bed, he himſelf alſo began to be of their Opinion, contrary to the <hi>general ſenſe of Mankind,</hi> when his guilty Conſcience forced him to tell his Son, <hi>That he had no good Title to the Crown;</hi> but he, not inferior to his Father in Ambition, ſnatched it from his Pillow, and plainly told him, <hi>That as he had got it by the Sword, ſo by the Sword he would keep it.</hi> And in truth, Doctor, your <hi>Title</hi> by <hi>Providence</hi> againſt Law, is <hi>Sword Title,</hi> and your <hi>Providential Kings, Sword-Kings;</hi> for in all Kingdoms the Sword is <hi>King,</hi> where their lawfull <hi>Prince</hi> is not; the Sword or Supream Force Rules all, and that Supream <hi>Cruſhing</hi> Force, which by God's permiſſion gets and keeps poſſeſſion, makes your <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. I have hitherto ſhewed you what Opinion many Wiſe and Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Men had of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and his Reign for want of Legal <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi> And I now proceed to ſhew the ſenſe that a whole Parliament had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66038:15"/> of him, and of his Son, and Grand-Son's Succeſſion, the latter ſitting in the Throne. This appears from <hi>Roll. Parl.</hi> 39 <hi>Henry</hi> VI. as it is in <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s <hi>Abridgement,</hi> or rather from the Record at large, as it is to be ſeen, as it was lately printed in an Anſwer, by a skillful and faithful hand, to <hi>The unreaſonableneſs of the new Separation upon account of the Oaths.</hi> This Roll gives an account, how <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> Father of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. brought to the Parliament Chamber in writing <hi>not a Petition</hi> but a <hi>Claim</hi> to the Crown, of which <hi>Henry</hi> had been long fully and quietly poſſeſſed; and his Title, which was only Succeſſion by Birth-right, being fully made appear, it was the Opinion of all the Lords, that <hi>it could not be defeated.</hi> That ſingle Title by Proximity of Blood was thought ſufficient to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede all the patch'd Titles of <hi>Henry,</hi> and all that could be ſaid in favour of him from the Oath of Allegiance which the People had made to him, from divers Acts of Parliament, whoſe Authority was laid againſt his Title; from the Entail of the Crown made by the Parliament upon his Father and his Heir; and laſtly from his Grandfather's Claim to the Crown, as right Inheretor from <hi>Henry</hi> III. which <hi>Richard</hi> proved to be falſe. And here, Doctor, I cannot but obſerve unto you, that among all the Pleas which <hi>Henry</hi> and his Counſellors made uſe of to defeat <hi>Richard</hi>'s Title, they never thought of your <hi>Divine Title from Providence,</hi> being ſo infatuated as not to attend to the <hi>General Senſe</hi> of Mankind. Wherefore, Doctor, either your Principles of Government are not the general Senſe of Mankind, or this Providential King, with his Privy-Council, and Great Council in <hi>Parliament,</hi> were all bewitch'd, that they could not think of them to ſtop the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Mouth. He adviſed with the greateſt Divines, and with the greateſt Men both among the Common and Civil Lawyers, and yet not one of them ſuggeſted the Title of Providence, or full Providential Poſſeſſion; but had they hit upon it, and urged it, <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> would have anſwered them as he did to their Plea taken from their Oaths, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that God's Commandments, which prefer Right, and Truth, and Juſtice, and not the Events of Providence, are the Rule for them to walk by, and <hi>that all Acts of the Eſtates againſt Law, Truth and Juſtice, are void and of no effect.</hi> The ſame is as true of all Poſſeſſion againſt Law, Truth and Juſtice, let it come by never ſuch amazing Providences; and therefore, Doctor, either your Notion of Providential Right, is not agreeable to the general ſenſe of Mankind, or elſe <hi>Henry</hi> and his whole Council were out of their Wits and common Senſes not to perceive it; but, in truth, Doctor, it became the general Senſe of Mankind only ſince the Victory of the <hi>Boyn</hi> made it become yours. From this Judgment of the Parliament 39 <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. I ſend you to the Judgment of another, 1 <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV. which after reciting the Lineal Title of <hi>Edward</hi> Son of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> from <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> and declaring how <hi>Henry Darby</hi> did rear War againſt <hi>Richard</hi> II. contrary to his Faith and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance. 2dly. That he took upon him Uſurpouſly the Crown, and Name of King, King <hi>Richard</hi> being <hi>in Priſon and living.</hi> 3dly. That againſt God's Law, Man's Legiance and Oath of Fidelity, and in a moſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66038:16"/> unnatural Tyranny he put him to Death: They then declare, <hi>That</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>rightfully amoved</hi> Henry VI. <hi>from his Occupation, Intruſion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Realm; and that he, and no other ought to be their Lord and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign by God's Law, Man's Law, and the Law of Nature; and that</hi> Henry Darby <hi>called K.</hi> Hen. IV. <hi>his Son called K.</hi> Hen. V. <hi>and his Son called K.</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry VI. <hi>had againſt all Law, Conſcience, and Cuſtom of the Realm, uſurped the Crown, and exerciſed the Government by unrighteous Intruſion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> and if they did ſo, then they had no Providential Divine Right. I muſt alſo obſerve unto you, that it was in this King's Reign that the diſtinction between the K. <hi>de facto</hi> to ſignifie the Uſurper, and the K. <hi>de jure</hi> to ſignifie the true legal K. was firſt uſed in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and I appeal to your own Conſcience, if it be not yet feared, whether that be <hi>an Arbitrary diſtinction, and to be</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">XXIX p. 17, 20.</note> 
               <hi>rejected as having no ſolid Foundation in Reaſon and Nature.</hi> I will maintain, that it hath as much Foundation in Reaſon and Nature, as that famous diſtinction in the Civil Law, betwixt <hi>Malae fidei,</hi> and <hi>Bonae fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei Poſſeſſor:</hi> But if your Reaſons about Providential Right be true, then this diſtinction alſo muſt be Arbitrary as to Poſſeſſion of Kingdoms, becauſe no Man in full Poſſeſſion, can be <hi>Malae fidei Poſſeſſor</hi> of a Crown. To theſe Authorities, let me add thoſe of the generality of the Nobility, Gentry, and Clergy of the late Uſurpations: They uſed the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Powers</hi> which you call Arbitrary, the ſame reaſoning which you call uncertain, and were of the ſame Opinion, which you ſay <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts the general Senſe of Mankind.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> whoſe Authority will be venerable, and much greater than yours, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Praelect.</hi> V.</note> is for that unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Allegiance to the Legal K. out of Poſſeſſion, which you moſt prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call <hi>Stupid and Slaviſh Allegiance,</hi> and in his Cenſure of <hi>Aſhcham,</hi> as one of your learned Anſwerers hath obſerved, charges your Opinion with the theſe immoral Conſequences. 1. <q>That it evidently tends to the taking away of all Chriſtian Fortitude and Suffering. 2. To the encouraging of daring and ambitious Spirits to attempt continual Innovations, with this confidence, that if they can poſſeſs themſelves of the Supream-Power, they ought to be ſubmitted to. 3. To the obſtructing unto the Oppreſſed Party all poſſible means, without a Miracle, of recovering his juſt <hi>Right,</hi> of which he ſhall have been illegally and unjuſtly diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsed. And laſtly, to the bringing in of Atheiſm, and the contempt of God and Religion.</q> The Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> was very ſenſible of this laſt Conſequence ſince he took the Oath, for he told the A.— B.— with great Gravity and Seriouſneſs, <hi>That he could not but admire the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God that ſo many took the Oath, and ſome, among whom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there are great and conſiderable Men have refuſed to take it; for we</hi> (ſaith he to my Lord) <hi>who have taken the Oath, have preſerved our Religion from Popery, and you who ſtand out, preſerve it from Atheiſm:</hi> and if they do, Doctor, as you alſo once thought, then their Opinion cannot contradict the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Senſe that Mankind have of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong.</hi> I am ſure the old <hi>Caviliers</hi> had the very ſame Senſe that <hi>theſe Men</hi> to their ſorrow have now; for they both called <hi>Charles</hi> II. <hi>King,</hi> and thought him to be ſo, tho' he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66038:16"/> was out of Poſseſſion, and out of the Land too. Nay, they took Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions from him as <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and ſought for him as their <hi>King;</hi> and not to make him ſo, as you Sophiſtically ſpeak in your <note n="*" place="margin">p. 27.</note> firſt Letter <hi>concerning the</hi> French <hi>Invaſion.</hi> Nay, the Convention that call'd him home, call'd him in as <hi>King,</hi> not to make him ſo; and dated their firſt Seſſion in the Twelfth year of his Reign, which, according to your Principles and Reaſonings, was but the Firſt. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> was one of the Members of it, and his Senſe and Opinion was point blank againſt yours, as you may find at large in his <note n="*" place="margin">p. 463. to 498.</note> 
               <hi>Plea for the Lords,</hi> and his <hi>Concordia Diſcors;</hi> and I cite him becauſe it was his ſtudied Opinion, and the Practice of his latter years was according to it, as appears alſo from a Paragraph or two in his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> to <hi>Cotton</hi>'s <hi>Abridgment,</hi> which I here declare, I produce againſt no Perſon nor no Authority but yours. <q>That all Parliaments and Ambitious Self-ſeekers in them, who under pretence of a Publick Reformation, Liberty, the Peoples Eaſe or Wellfare, have by indirect Surmiſe, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, Practices, Force, and new Devices, moſt Uſurped upon the lawfull Prerogatives of their <hi>Kings,</hi> or the Perſons, Lives, Offices, or Eſtates of ſuch Nobles, Great Officers, and other perſons of a contrary Party, whom they moſt dreaded, maligned, and which have impoſed new Oaths and Engagements on the Members to ſecure, perpetuate, and make irrevocable their own Acts, Judgments, and unrighteous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, have always proved moſt Abortive, Succeſsleſs, Pernicious to themſelves, and the activeſt Inſtruments in them; the Parliaments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being commonly totally Repealed, Null'd, and the Grandees in them Suppreſſed, Impeached, Condemned, Deſtroyed as Traytors and Enemies to the Publick, in the very next ſucceeding Parliaments, or not very long after. That <hi>Kings</hi> created, and ſet up meerly by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and their own Power in them, without any true Hereditary Title, have ſeldom anſwered the Lords and Commons Expectations in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their juſt Laws, Liberties, and Anſwers to their Petitions; yea, themſelves at laſt branded for Tyrants, Traitors, Murderers, Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; their Poſterities Impeached of High Treaſon, and diſinherited of the Crown by ſucceeding <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as you may read at large in the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From theſe three laſt Obſervations, we may learn, that as <hi>Parliaments</hi> are the beſt of all Courts, Councils, when duly Summoned, Conven'd, Conſtituted, Ordered, and kept within their legal Bounds: So they become the greateſt Miſchiefs and Grievances to the Kingdom, when like the Ocean they overflow their Banks, or degenerate and become, through Sedition, Malice, Fear, or Infatuation by Divine Juſtice, Promoters of corrupt ſiniſter Ends, or Accompliſhers of the private Deſigns and ambitious Intereſts of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, under the diſguiſe of publick Reformation, Liberty, Safety, and Sentlement.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee, Doctor, here, how Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> diſtinguiſhes between legal <hi>Kings</hi> by Hereditary Title, and <hi>Kings</hi> that are not legal; and between <hi>Parliaments</hi> Convened and acting legally, from <hi>Parliaments</hi> that are not ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66038:17"/> Conven'd, and do not ſo Act: But in your <hi>Providential Hypotheſis,</hi> which muſt damn all <hi>ſuch diſtinctions as Groundleſs and Arbitrary,</hi> it is enough that any Man, <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> or <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> be ſet up for King by the Eſtates of the Realm, howſoever Conven'd and Acting. Once the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of this Realm did moſt illegally call in a <hi>French</hi> King, and ſet him up in the Throne, and ſwear Fealty to him; and if in the late deſigned <hi>French</hi> Invaſion, which if God had thought fit might have ſucceeded, they had ſet up the <hi>great Oppreſſor of the Liberties of Europe;</hi> then, according to your Doctrine, he muſt have been King, and by your Principles, and <hi>all the ſeriouſneſs which the Subject of the Laſt Judgment requires,</hi> you muſt and would have profeſſed, without any regard to the Recognitions of their Majeſties right, that <hi>you were his moſt faithful Subject and Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Authority of Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> I ſhall add that of Judg <hi>Jenkins,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt the Power of the two Houſes, when they had made the King their Priſoner, and uſurped his Sovereign Authority, and had power to <hi>cruſh</hi> his Majeſty, and much more any other Man in the Kingdom. Shortly after Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> printed his <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> and a Juſtification of it from Law, in which he declared he ſhould hold it a great Honour to dye for the <hi>honourable and holy Laws of the Land.</hi> It was for the King then and his Authority, that he ſtood up againſt the <hi>Powers in being,</hi> who were then in your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and he aſserted before them, <hi>That Allegiance follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King's natural Perſon, then Priſoner at</hi> Holmby. And as for the times before him he declared, that all <hi>Depoſers</hi> of Kings were <hi>Traitors,</hi> that <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> IV. was an Uſurper, and that <hi>Kings de facto</hi> are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> that come in by the Conſent of the People. This is the Doctrine of Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> of famous Memory; but yours, Doctor, is the ſcandalous Doctrine of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Holy Common-wealth, as has been obſerved by a plain honeſt Layman, in a <note n="†" place="margin">Providence and Precept</note> Book which he wrote againſt you, and which I believe you can never anſwer. I wonder how Dr. <hi>Grove,</hi> your old Acquaintance, who wrote againſt <hi>Jenkins,</hi> takes it, to have his <hi>Reaſonings</hi> condemned by you, as contrary to the general Senſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; they were received with great Applauſe by all wiſe and conſidering Churchmen, when they were firſt publiſhed, and I do not hear he hath retracted them: And therefore, Doctor, give me leave to make uſe of his Teſtimony, among others, to prove that the Reaſonings of <hi>Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves</hi> are not contrary to the general Senſe of Mankind. To theſe common Lawyers let me add the Authority of one Civilian, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir <hi>John Hayward,</hi> in his Anſwer to the <hi>Firſt Part of a Conference con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Succeſſion,</hi> by <hi>R. Doleman;</hi> and to theſe ſingle Authorities that of all the Judges in the famous Caſe of the <hi>Poſtnati,</hi> which two of your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>d.</hi> p. 101. <hi>c.</hi> p. 37.</note> Adverſaries have cited againſt you, <hi>(viz.) That Allegiance follows the natural Perſon of the King,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Sir <hi>Francs Moorts</hi> Reports 79.</note> 
               <hi>it is not taken away, though the King is expulſed by Force, and another uſurps.</hi> When you were firſt acquainted with this Opinion of the Judges by a learned Lawyer, you expreſs'd your Satisfaction with Joy, and talkt of printing the diſcovery; but ſince you have taken the Oath their Authority ſignifies not a Straw; for you are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66038:17"/> become the true Son of your Sire <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who was above all Authority but his own. To theſe Lawyers of our own Countrey I beg leave to add that of two or three foreign Lawyers, whereof two are <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Men, the learned <hi>Craigy,</hi> and Sir. <hi>George Mackenzy;</hi> the former's Opinion is to be ſeen in a learned MS. of his, entituled <hi>Thomae Cragii de Jure Succeſſionis Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Angliae Libriduo, adverſus Sophiſmata Perſonati Dolemani, quibus non ſolum Jura Succeſſionis in Regnis, ſed etiam ipſorum Regum Sſ. Auctoritatem nititur evertere.</hi> The Opinion of the latter is to be read in his <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S REG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> or Defence of the Succeſſion in <hi>Scotland,</hi>— and as he wrote in that Book, ſo he lived and dyed a faithfull Subject, or if you will, Doctor, <hi>a ſtupid Slave of Loyalty;</hi> for he was one of <hi>theſe Men:</hi> And it is well for you that he dyed when he did; for had he ſurvived in Health, you, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Writers would, as I have been informed, have ſoon heard from him. The third is a <hi>Dutch</hi> Man of no ſmall Authority, even <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> who was a wiſe and conſidering Man indeed, and did not uſe to write Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to the general Senſe of Mankind; but yet he, as you have been told already by a very learned <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>aa.</hi> p. 93.</note> Man, ſaith expreſly in contradiction to your Doctrine, <note n="†" place="margin">De Jar. Bell. &amp; Pac. <hi>l. 1. c. 14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that it is lawfull to kill an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, if it be with the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of him that hath the Right to govern, whether that Right be in the King, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or the People. And to theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we are to reckon the Tutors and Guardians of young Princes, as</hi> Jehoiada <hi>was to</hi> Joaſh <hi>when he depoſed</hi> Athaliah. From theſe Men, whom you did not know, I proceed to ſome of your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and I hope, Doctor, you will not take it ill to hear them ſpeak. The firſt ſhall be Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> now Bp. of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> who is reputed a wiſe and conſidering Man, and Writer, that did not uſe to write Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to the general Senſe of Mankind; and yet in ſeveral places of his <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> p. 58, 80, 81, 83, 85.</note> 
               <hi>Grand Queſtion</hi> he hath aſſerted, that ſeveral Acts of Parliament made by <hi>Edward</hi> III. in his Father's life time, and by <hi>Henry</hi> IV. were <hi>null</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> becauſe they were Uſurpers, or in your Language Providential, but not Legal Kings. And in his Sermon before the Commons, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 13.—71. He tells them <hi>that Providence doth not found any Right of Dominion, but onely ſhews, that when God pleaſes to make uſe of perſons as Scourges, he gives them Succeſs above their hopes; but Succeſs gives them no Right.</hi> The next is Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> who in the firſt Part of the <hi>Hiſtory of the Refarmation</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> IV. as a Traitor and Uſurper, and how doubtfully he ſpeaks of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Sermon before the Prince at St. <hi>James's,</hi> you may remember as well as I. The third is Dr. <hi>Comber,</hi> who, as I hear, confeſſeth that he and others went too far; but however I that think the Doctor as good an Author before as ſince the Revolution, will not balk his Authority, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince he hath retracted nothing publickly; and he ſaith on the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect for the King, <q>That his Friends are our Friends, and his Enemies our Enemies; for whoever attempts to ſmite the Sheepherd, ſeeks to deſtroy the Sheep, and he is a mortal Foe to the whole Nation. I know nothing ſo common with Rebels and Uſurpers, as to pretend Love to thoſe they would ſtir up againſt their lawfull Prince; but it appears to be Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Covetouſneſs in the latter end; and ſuch Perſons deſign to riſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66038:18"/> by the fall of many thouſands. Or if Religion be the ground of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, beſides our late ſad Experience, Reaſon will tell us, that War and Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Injuſtice and Cruelty, can never lodge in thoſe Breaſts where that pure and peaceable Quality doth dwell. If it be a <hi>foreign Prince</hi> that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth our King, he is a Robber, and unjuſt, to invade his Neighbour's Rights: If he be a <hi>Subject</hi> who riſeth againſt his Sovereign, he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Chriſtianity with his Allegiance, and is to be eſteemed a troubler of our <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Therefore whoſoever they be that <hi>are Enemies to the King,</hi> or whatſoever the pretence be, we wiſh they may never proſper in that black Impiety of <hi>unjuſt Invaſion,</hi> or unchriſtian Rebellion.</q> How like a Saint, and an excellent Caſuiſt, doth the Doctor write here; but how this agrees with his Speeches, Letters, and Actions, ſince the <hi>Inſurrection at</hi> York, Time, and Opportunity of Printing will ſhew. The fourth is Dr. <hi>Tenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who had occaſion to conſider your Doctrine, long before it was yours, in his Book entituled <hi>the Creed of Mr.</hi> Hobbs <hi>examined.</hi> 
               <q>In his Epiſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to that Book, ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> hath framed a Model of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment pernicious in its conſequence to all Nations, and injurious to the Right of his preſent Majeſty; for he taught the People ſoon after the Martyrdom of his Royal Father, that his Title was extinguiſhed when his Adherents were ſubdued; and that the Parliament had the Right for this very reaſon, becauſe it had Poſſeſſion. And in <hi>Art.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 156. firſt Edit. It is not for you to pretend to Loyalty who place Right in Force, and teach the People to aſſiſt the Uſurper with active Compliance againſt a diſpoſſeſſed Prince, and not merely to live at all adventure in his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, without owning the Protection by unlawfull Oaths, or by run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into Arms againſt the dethron'd Sovereign. And <hi>p.</hi> 157. I ſay then again, that you give Encouragement to Uſurpers, and alſo when Civil Diſorders are on foot, as it happens too frequent in all States, you hereby move ſuch People as are yet on the ſide of their lawfull Prince, whoſe Affairs they ſee declining, ſtreightway to join themſelves to the more proſperous Party, and help to overturn thoſe Thrones of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty to which a while before they proſtrated themſelves.—The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thus miſ-inſtructed will imitate thoſe Idolatrous Heathens, who for ſome years worſhipped a Goddeſs made faſt unto a Tree; but aſſoon as the Tree began by Age and Tempeſt to appear decaying, they paid no farther devotion to their Deity, neither would they come within the ſhadow of the Oak or Image.</q> You ſee, Doctor, how this Author wrote then againſt <hi>Hobbs,</hi> juſt as <hi>ſome among <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> write now againſt you; and as well as you are acquainted with him, yet I believe he would ſwell as big at you, as at the ſight of any <hi>Jacobite,</hi> if you ſhould tell him, that the moſt <hi>ſober and conſidering Men rejected his Reaſonings as contradictory to the general ſenſe of mankind.</hi> The laſt Authority, Doctor, is your Great and Dear Self, who not long ſince was a Man of thoſe Reaſonings, and that Opinion by which <hi>ſome among our ſelves</hi> have the impudence, ſince you were of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Judgment, to contradict the general ſenſe of Mankind. I ſhall not trouble you with a review of your Writings before the Revolution, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66038:18"/> take you as you were almoſt two years after it, whilſt you were under the <hi>ſtupid Diſpenſation</hi> of ſlaviſh Loyalty, nor as yet had diſcover'd the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Providence, but were as zealous as any of <hi>theſe Men</hi> to deferd Laws and legal Rights againſt the Events of it; but whether <hi>factiouſly</hi> or <hi>not factiouſly,</hi> as you <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vindic.</hi> p. 79, 80.</note> pretend, ſome matters of Fact will ſhew. I ſhall not inſiſt on the half Sheet you publiſhed at the ſitting down of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, againſt making the P. of <hi>Orange</hi> King; but onely obſerve, that then you ſuppoſed the Throne to be full; and aſſerted, That the Eſtates then convened could not give him the Crown, becauſe it was not theirs to give. A little after this you wrote the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Enquiry, which I mentioned before, in which you aſſert, in oppoſition to the <hi>Doctor,</hi> that King <hi>James</hi> was <hi>a King not by governing well, but by Birth right, and could no more ceaſe to be King by governing ill, than a Traitor or a Rebel ceaſe to be a Subject:</hi> And this you proved from the paternal Relation of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who never ceaſe to be a Father, how great a Tyrant ſoever he be. You alſo challenged the <hi>Doctor</hi> there, to ſhew you any Law of God, or our Country, which <hi>upon any Cauſe</hi> diſſolves our Allegiance, and aſſerted, <hi>that the Deſcent of the Crown muſt be governed by the Laws of the Land.</hi> I muſt here tell the Reader, that this Anſwer of yours was never publiſhed, leſt he ſhould loſe his labour in enquiring after it; for though it was printed, yet whether at <hi>Xantippe</hi>'s Inſtance, or any other Cauſe of Fear, you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed all the Coppies but two, which happened to get abroad, and one of thoſe fell into my Hands. After this, on the 8th of <hi>April</hi> following, you went to a learned Gentleman, to perſuade him <hi>not to be preſent at the Coronation;</hi> and though their Majeſties had been recognized by the Eſtates, and were then in full Providential Poſſeſſion, yet you told him, you had rather take the Oath twenty times than bear a part in it: But about the beginning of <hi>May</hi> after you wrote a Diſcourſe for taking the Oaths, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Lawfulneſs of taking the New Oath of Allegiance to King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>ſtated upon the ſtricteſt Principles of Church of</hi> England <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty;</hi> and after you had finiſhed it you ſent it, as I underſtand by a Letter from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> to Dr. <hi>Bu</hi>— (by which I underſtand Dr. <hi>Burnet;</hi>) but that Diſcourſe plainly <hi>ſuppoſing the Government to be an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> and that <hi>Non-reſiſtence was reſerved as a Duty to King</hi> James, from whom it could not be ſuſpended, it was not thought fit to be publiſhed. This Book was ſeen and peruſed by many, particularly two or three Clergymen at <hi>Tunbridge</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> following ſaid they had read it: But to doe you Juſtice, <hi>Doctor,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this you did all you could to ſuppreſs it, becauſe it would not hold; but it was now too late to attempt the ſuppreſſion of it, for Copies had got abroad into ſeveral Hands, and I have one of them at your Ladies Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who I ſuppoſe was not againſt writing of it. Upon Conviction this Paper would not hold, then you grew very warm againſt the Oath; for in the latter end of <hi>June,</hi> or beginning of <hi>July,</hi> you affirmed, <hi>that the taking of it was not onely a recognizing, but making the P. of</hi> Orange <hi>King;</hi> (as yet then Providence had not made him ſo:) adding, <hi>that though you could actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally forbear aſſiſting King</hi> James, <hi>yet you could not ſwear never to aſſiſt him, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66038:19"/> being not conſiſtent with an Acknowledgment of his Right; and that the more you thought of the Oath the worſe you liked it, and would have nothing to doe with it;</hi> Remember this, good <hi>Doctor,</hi> and then conſider if it doth not become a Man that ſaid and did ſuch things then to rant and ſwagger againſt <hi>ſome among our ſelves</hi> now. It was now about this time that you were in the highth of your Fevour againſt the Government and the Oaths, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it ſelf by many Symptomes, upon ſeveral occaſions: When you firſt heard the News of a Faſt, which happened to be at your Houſe in the <hi>Temple, How! a Faſt!</hi> ſaid you; <hi>I'll warrant you we ſhall have dainty Prayers: Prayers,</hi> ſaid Dr. <hi>Sharp, that I am more affraid of than the Oaths. And what! Muſt we have Sermons too? I'll give them a Sermon that they ſhall not thank me for;</hi> and accordingly you did ſo: Your Text I remember was, <hi>The Lord is a Man of War, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name;</hi> and then you preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed contrary point blank to what you have ſince printed; and the drift of your Diſcourſe was ſo plainly levelled againſt the Government, and the Intention of the day, that you gave great Offence to their Majeſties good Subjects, who filled the Town with Complaints againſt you; but you va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued not that, but was pleaſed with it, delighting to give <hi>ſome among us</hi> an account of what you had preached, and how you had met with them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time alſo you wrote a Diſcourſe againſt taking the Oaths, which you ſhewed to a Learned and Reverend Divine on the 29th of <hi>July.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was your Letter to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> whoſe Anſwer to it you deſpiſed, as Stuff that did not deſerve a Reply; though one, who ſaw it, ſaith you ſtole your Argument from <hi>Jaddus,</hi> and other things out of it, which you have put in your <hi>Caſe of Allegiance.</hi> In <hi>Auguſt</hi> out comes the firſt part of the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience,</hi> which you careſſed into the World, and were ſo taken with it, that you went to a very learned Man, who ſince became your Antagoniſt, to pray him to write a Sheet of Concluſions, not againſt <hi>ſome,</hi> but againſt <hi>other</hi> men, upon the Doctrines and Principles col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in it; and that he might not miſtake your deſign, you left it in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with him, and he ſtill hath the Original in the following Words, <hi>The Doctrine of Nonreſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience is founded on an irreſible Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; conſider then what are the Rights of an irreſiſtible Authority, and what the Duties of Paſſive Obedience.</hi> 1. <hi>The Rights of Sovereign and irreſiſtible Authority are that he cannot forfeit his Crown, that he cannot be judged or depoſed by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; (and Abdication and Deſertion are but other names for this;) and therefore when once King, he is always ſo till Death, or voluntary or legal Reſignation.</hi> 2. <hi>Nonreſiſtence does not onely ſignifie not to fight againſt the King, but,</hi> 1. <hi>That upon no pretence we muſt renounce his Right.</hi> 2. <hi>We muſt never ſet his Crown upon another's Head.</hi> 3. <hi>We muſt not transfer our Allegiance to another.</hi> In this Month alſo dyed the Bp. of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> of everlaſting Memory, to whom, as a Perſon of Honor can teſtifie, you went about four or five days before he dyed, to move him to make his <hi>Declaration.</hi> About the ſame time you ſent a Paper to <hi>Oxford</hi> againſt taking the Oath; I have forgot the Title of it, but I remember a paſſage in it to this purpoſe, That as Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſeize upon the Lands, and Houſes, and Fortifications of the King for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66038:19"/> their own uſe, and turn them to their own Service againſt Law; ſo againſt Law they ſeize upon the Laws themſelves, and uſe them againſt their firſt Intention to their own Service, and the deſtruction of the King and his faithfull Subjects, for whoſe defence they were made, About the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>September</hi> you wrote an Apology for the Nonſwearers, which you deſigned for your Maſterpiece; and in <hi>December</hi> following a malitious Pamphlet coming out againſt the Biſhops, entituled <hi>A Letter out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> &amp;c. you began an Anſwer to it in defence of them; but ſtaying out too long where you wrote it, Mrs. <hi>Satan and Sherlock</hi> took you to task, and ſucceeded ſo well, as to make you confeſs where you had been, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what, and then it was no great Conqueſt to make you ſend for your Papers by ſix a Clock next morning, and offer them as an Holocauſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone her diſpleaſure. In all this time that you were ſo warm and zealous againſt the Oath, you helped to diſperſe the few ſmall Pamphlets that were printed againſt taking of it, and expreſſed much trouble, that others that were larger could not get abroad; particularly you were very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for Printing <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance to a King in Poſſeſſion,</hi> which you then thought an admirable Piece, and upon all occaſions you were wont to expreſs your Affection and Duty to King <hi>James,</hi> and your deſire for his Return; as by drinking to his Health and happy Reſtauration, and at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times by ſending up devout Ejaculations for it, and ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> if others did ſo: And, Sir, your own Memory and your Conſcience can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you that theſe are Truths, and no Inventions; and how they agree with your Preface to your <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> and the Concluſion of your Vindication of it, let the Readers, and eſpecially the Lawyers, judge. In that Preface you tell us, that you had ſtuck in your former Opinion to this day, had you not been relieved by Bp. <hi>Overall</hi>'s <hi>Convocation-Book:</hi> But how did that relieve you? Or when did the pretended Doctrine in it begin to operate on your Underſtanding, and remove your former difficulty? I am ſure that it was ſent you Sheet by Sheet from the Preſs, and had no Operation upon you at the firſt reading; but happening to lie in the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller's Shop ſome time before it was Publiſhed, for want of the Preface; the News of it brought abundance of Clergy-Men, and others, to read it there, and ſome that had taken the Oaths thinking theſe Paſſages made for them, they diſcovered them, and formed Arguments from them to juſtfy their own Complyance, but you diſpiſed them for wreſting the Words of the Convocation, and uſed to obſerve upon that occaſion, how Men would be glad of any pretences, and catch at any Twiggs to bear up themſelves againſt their own Conſciences. This was in <hi>December</hi> before you took the Oaths, and no Body that I ever met with perceived you to be of any other Opinion 'till after the <hi>Victory of the Boyne:</hi> For in that interim you behaved your ſelf among your Brethren, as you had done formerly, particularly you ſhewed Complacency enough at the Victory which the French had over us by Sea, in hopes it would haſten another Revolution; and accordingly taking Horſe at a Gentleman's Door, who then thought you deſerved a better; you told him, that you now hoped by <hi>Michaelmas</hi> to have a better
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66038:20"/> Horſe. This was but a little while before the News of the <hi>Boyne</hi> Victory came to Town, and then <hi>Doctor</hi> it was that Bp. <hi>Overall</hi>'s Book <hi>gave you greater Freedom and Liberty of Thinking,</hi> then you firſt diſcovered your New Notions, and Inclinations to your Brethren, then you thought it high time to emancipate your ſelf from your <hi>ſtupid Church of</hi> England <hi>Loyalty, and the ſlaviſh Principles of it, the Rights of irreſiſtible Authority, and the Duties of Paſſive Obedience:</hi> All vaniſhed then upon New Light; for <hi>Egeria</hi> appear'd to you upon the Banks of the <hi>Boyne,</hi> and inſpired you with New and Freer Notions, and ſhewed you in that glorious Scene, how your former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings <hi>contradicted the General Senſe of Mankind, and had no foundation in Reaſon or Nature,</hi> and revealed unto you a Divine and ſafer Principle upon which you might Swear Allegiance, without the Imputation of Apoſtacy or renouncing the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to <hi>WILHELM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S NASS. ANG. SCOT. HIBER. ADEODAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and alſo ſwear it back again to King <hi>James,</hi> if ever he ſhould recover the Throne in a recuperative War. But to make out your <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of a Thorough Settlement the better, you were willing alſo to have <hi>Limerick</hi> taken before you took the Oath; and therefore you wrote to a Friend then at <hi>Dublin,</hi> to ſend you word aſſoon as that Town was taken, becauſe, as he knew, it concerned you much to know it. But, <hi>Doctor,</hi> as you ſay of the <hi>Nature of things</hi> that Town was <hi>pretty ſtubborn,</hi> and you were in haſte, and could not ſtay for the Surrender of it; but the new Settlement was ſufficient for your purpoſe without it, or perhaps the R.R. <hi>Welch Prophet</hi> aſſured you it would be taken, and that was enough to a willing and well diſpoſed Mind. And now, <hi>Doctor,</hi> upon an impartial Review of your former Principles and Practice, will you ſeriouſly tell me, did you not think your ſelf as wiſe and conſidering a Man before you took the Oaths as ſince? And could you well have born it, if any Man had then dogmatically told you, that <hi>your Reaſonings were uncertain, and that your Opinion was contrary to the General Senſe of Mankind, or that it was rejected by the moſt ſober and conſidering Men?</hi> Alas! What ſhall we inferiour Mortals and <hi>little Writers</hi> do, thus to have <hi>Sherlock</hi> againſt <hi>Sherlock?</hi> Which of the two ſhall we believe? <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſaying, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> unſaying what he ſaid, and for what he ſuffered? <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> confeſſing, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> retracting his Confeſſion? <hi>Sherlock</hi> deprived, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> reſtored, and higher preferred? <hi>Sherlock</hi> baffling others, or <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> by others miſerably baffled? <hi>Sherlock</hi> with the Generality of Writers, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> againſt the Generality of them? <hi>Sherlock</hi> with the learned and venerable Writers of Authority, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> with a few little fanatical Writers of no Authority? <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſaying and proving, or <hi>Sherlock</hi> barely ſaying and appealing, but not proving what he ſaith? But as the learned Author of the Reply to your Vindication <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>aa.</hi> p. 106, 111. See alſo p. 11.</note> hath obſerved, methinks you ſhould have but little Stomach to appeal to the general Senſe of Mankind, to which your fundamental Doctrine, and the Arguments that ſupport it, are contrary, except <hi>John Goodwin</hi> and his Fellows be the Senſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And in another <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>a.</hi> Poſtſcript.</note> place he obſerves, that when he had urged you in his firſt Book to ſhew any one approved Author of your ſide the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66038:20"/> you only produced two, <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> againſt the firſt of which he tells you there is juſt Exception, and that the other is directly againſt you. And it is now a year ſince his Anſwer came out, and any Man of tolerable Modeſty would have produced more and better Authors on his ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had aſſerted from the Pulpit and the Preſs, that <hi>his Adverſary's Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings were rejected by the moſt ſober and conſidering Men, and contradicted the general Senſe of Mankind.</hi> For God's ſake, <hi>Doctor,</hi> what privilege have you above other Men thus to impoſe upon the World, and treat your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries at this rate? Have your new Principles ſet you free from the ſlaviſh Doctrine of Modeſty as well as that of Loyalty? Or have you acquired the Authority of an Oracle that Mankind is bound to receive Maxims from you, and to believe without examining what you ſay? Perhaps you may be prolocutor the next ſitting of the Convocation; or if you have not the Chair, you will have the next Seat to it; and notwithſtanding this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and ſo many <hi>London Livings</hi> in your Diſpoſal, I deſire and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge you to propoſe your <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and the Reaſonings that ſupport it, to the two Houſes, to try whether they will approve or condemn it. Their Authority you will needs allow to be great and venerable, and I dare appeal to them as Judges of the Controverſy, not doubting but that they will be of the ſame Mind with the <hi>Convocation at Oxford,</hi> where the Doctors and Maſters, in <hi>July</hi> 1683, damned your Doctrine in the Cenſure of the following Propoſition, which in the <hi>Decree</hi> runs in theſe Words, —<hi>Poſſeſſion and Strength give a Right to Govern, and Succeſs in a Cauſe or Enterprize, proclaims it to be lawful and juſt; to juſtify it is to comply with the Will of God, becauſe it is to follow the Conduct of his Providence.</hi> And then in the Margent over againſt it, they cite <hi>Hobbs, Owen, Baxter</hi> and <hi>Jenkins;</hi> and in the next Impreſſion I hope they will put your Name in that glorious Company, to ſhew the Senſe of Mankind. I ground my Confidence, in this Appeal, upon Diſcourſes which I, and others, have had with ſeveral worthy Members of the Convocation, who have been ſo free as to tell us that they could not be of your Opinion; nay ſome of them have told me frankly, that they abhorred your Principle, and could never have taken the Oath upon it: I believe you would be angry with them ſhould I tell you their Names; but I do not know why they may not contradict you, as well as you have contradicted the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph;</hi> for, contrary to his Sermon, entituled <hi>God's ways of diſpoſing Kingdoms,</hi> which he preached before the Queen, You, in your <hi>Faſt-Sermon</hi> preached not long after, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her, in <hi>June,</hi> the laſt year, and printed, as his was, by her <hi>Majeſties Special Command,</hi> tell us, That <hi>God doth not always determine what is right and wrong by the Events of War, for he is the Sovereign Judge of the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and may often puniſh a wicked Nation, by unjuſt Oppreſſors, as he did the Iſraelites.</hi> The good Lord be merciful to the poor <hi>Jacobites,</hi> who are like never to be converted at this rate, when one of you ſo apparently contradicts another, and each part of the Contradiction hath Royal Authority on its ſide. I do not ſay that you deſignedly contradicted the Biſhop, and I had almoſt ſaid your ſelf too, for that Propoſition ſeems to look very foul upon your
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66038:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:66038:21"/>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66038:22"/> Doctrine of Providence, and almoſt needs an Explication; and in good Truth <hi>Doctor,</hi> the Senſe of Mankind, and the natural Notions, are on the other ſide of the Controverſy, and if you do not carefully prevent them, they will obtrude upon you, and carry you to contradict your ſelf, as your Father <hi>Hobs</hi> did in <hi>his Hiſtory of the Civil Wars,</hi> who before he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it, run into the <hi>Arbitrary</hi> diſtinction betwixt Supream Strength and Right to govern: For to the Queſtion, Who had the Supream Power when there was no Parliament?<note place="margin">P. 252.</note> 
               <hi>If by Power</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you mean the Right to Govern,</hi> no Body had it; but if you mean <hi>the Supream Strength,</hi> that was clearly in <hi>Cromwel,</hi> who was obeyed as General of the Forces in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, <hi>Doctor,</hi> I ſtopt a little to review the Authorities I have brought againſt you; and I find, that as a Man who has many Witneſſes at a Tryal, may forget to call ſome; ſo I have forgot two Teſtimonies againſt you, which I deſire may be now heard ſpeak. The firſt is the Teſtimony of the Judges and Peers in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time; and the ſecond is that of the Firſt Parliament of <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. p. 32, 33.</note> The former, at the Tryal of the Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> made Anſwer to the Duke, Querying by way of Plea, Whether a Man acting by the Authority of the Great Seal, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Privy Council, could become thereby Guilty of Treaſon? That the Great Seal of One that was not Lawful Queen, could give no Authority nor Indemnity to thoſe that acted on ſuch a Warrant. The latter, in ſeveral of their Acts, as in that for a <hi>Poll towards reducing</hi> Ireland, 1 Gul. &amp; Mar, 1 May 1689. and that for the <hi>Relief of their Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects in</hi> Ireland, 1 Gul. &amp; Mar. Jan. 27. 1689. declared the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> then under King <hi>James'</hi> Poſſeſſion, and actual Government, to owe their Obedience to King <hi>William,</hi> and for breach thereof to be Rebels; though King <hi>James</hi> had been ſolemnly recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm.</p>
            <p>But now, Doctor, after all theſe Teſtimonies againſt you, perhaps you will reply, that theſe are only Teſtimonies, as <hi>to the Senſe,</hi> but not <hi>as to the Practiſe of Men;</hi> whereas you have Aſſerted the <hi>Reaſonings of ſome among our ſelves,</hi> to be not only againſt the General Senſe, but the General Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Mankind, in all Revolutions, and that this is apparently on your ſide: But if you, or any for you, object this againſt me, I pray you to conſider, that the Practiſes of Men are to be tryed by Principles, and not Principles by the General Practiſes of men; for Mankind, <hi>Doctor,</hi> is a very corrupt Creature, apt to act againſt the moſt acknowledged Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Truth and Falſhood, Good and Evil,</hi> which God has engraven on all men's hearts, as the Common Law, or Common Senſe, or Common Notions of all mankind. And as they will act againſt theſe Common Notions, or the Law of Nature, ſo will they act againſt the Law of Grace, or the Notions of revealed Religion; more eſpecially they will act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both in times of Perſecution, when Eaſe, Safety, Honour, and Preferment, attend thoſe who take part with Error againſt Truth, and Wrong againſt Right; and Danger, Trouble, Diſgrace, and poverty,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66038:22"/> thoſe who ſide with Truth againſt Errour, and Right againſt Wrong. In ſuch hard Caſes, <hi>Doctor,</hi> few will chooſe the Suffering ſide; but the generality of men will act, not only againſt the general Senſe of mankind, but againſt the inward Sence and Checks of their own Conſciences; as in the Idolatrous Reign of <hi>Ahab,</hi> when Idolatry was the general practiſe of the Jews; in the <hi>Arrian</hi> Reign of <hi>Valens,</hi> when the <hi>Arrian</hi> Doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Jeſus to be true God, was the general profeſſion, and <hi>Arrian</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the general practiſe of Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Simon Dew</hi>'s Journal, p. 23.</note> in the Popiſh Reign of Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> when all the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but one hundred ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven, turn'd Papiſts after Popery was <hi>throughly ſettled</hi> by Parliament, and <hi>recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm,</hi> and ſo became the Providential Religion of the Church; ſo in the late <hi>French</hi> Perſecution, the generality of Proteſtants, preferring Eaſe and Safety before a good Conſcience, turn'd Converts to Popery againſt their own Faith and Principles; and as for thoſe few which did not, the Bp. of <hi>Meaux</hi> might have told them, That they <hi>had nothing to ſupport them but ſome uncertain Reaſonings which contradict the general Practice of Mankind in all Revolutions of Religion.</hi> You ſee, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, what a poor Argument the general <hi>Practice</hi> of mankind is in Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where the great majority will go with the Stream of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment:</hi> And therefore we are bid not to follow a multitude to doe Evil; but to ſtick to <hi>Principles</hi> againſt Men's <hi>Practices,</hi> and the <hi>Precepts</hi> of natural and revealed Religion againſt Men's <hi>Examples,</hi> be they never ſo many and great: For in truth, Doctor, few Men will doe their duty in any kind; and therefore there are but few that will be ſaved, eſpecially in ſuch an Age of latitude as this, wherein <hi>looſe Principles</hi> make <hi>looſe Practices;</hi> ſo that you will find very few Men of ſtrict, or if you pleaſe, Doctor, of <hi>ſtupid</hi> and <hi>ſlaviſh Vertue.</hi> In particular, if you pleaſe, to look about, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you will find almoſt as few men of ſtupid and ſlaviſh Sobriety, or ſtupid and ſlaviſh Chaſtity, as of ſtupid and ſlaviſh Loyalty. Nay, if the general Complaints be true, there are but very few of <hi>ſtupid and ſlaviſh Justice and Honeſty:</hi> For why ſhould a Man of Honour (as the Cardinal ſaid) be a Slave to his Word, or to his Oath either, eſpecially of late,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Serm. of Hell-Torments.</note> ſince <hi>we can hardly tell how to reconcile the eternal Miſery of Hell with the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Goodneſs of God, who, notwithſtanding all his Threatenings of it in Scripture, is free to doe what he pleaſes.</hi> But this, Doctor, doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you, but to ſome of thoſe <hi>Nine Men,</hi> who you told <note n="*" place="margin">In a Letter to a Friend, containing ſome Queries about the New Commiſſion for making Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the Liturgy, Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Church of <hi>England; ſent to the Preſs by Dr.</hi> Sherlock, <hi>and publiſhed a little before the firſt Sitting of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
               </note> us, not long before you took the Oath, <hi>had Latitude enough to conform to a Church</hi> de facto <hi>which had Power on its ſide, and Tenderneſs and Moderation enough to part with any thing but their Church Preferments. When you were at the Writing of that Letter,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">p 5.</note> 
               <hi>the A. Bp. and other Biſhops and Clergymen under Suſpenſion, were as eminent for a prudent and well tempered Zeal, as for their conſtant Loyalty;</hi> but now their well tempered Zeal, though not one degree altered from its Temper, is <hi>factious,</hi> and their conſtant Loyalty <hi>ſtupid and ſlaviſh Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> and what elſe you will hereafter be pleaſed to call it or them.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:66038:23"/>13. Having now, I hope, vindicated the Opinions and Reaſonings of ſome <hi>among our ſelves</hi> from Singularity and Novelty, by ſhewing that they do not contradict the general Senſe of Mankind, but are the very Senſe of the wiſeſt and beſt part of it; I come now to examine what you ſay, for I cannot call what you ſay Arguments againſt them,<note place="margin">p. 15.</note> who, as you tell the World, <hi>withdraw</hi> from our Communion, becauſe we pray for K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary:</hi> but they ſay, and I fear are able to prove it too, that it is you that have withdrawn from them and their Communion, and that the Schiſm, and the cauſes of it, is in you and not in them. But to let that paſs, you aſſert that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in your Text, <hi>makes no difference of Kings,</hi> but that <hi>they</hi> do; but I tell you, Sir, that they make as little difference as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for they grant that he commands us to pray for all Kings; but then they ſay that the Uſurpers of Kingdoms, as long as they remain ſo, are not Kings, nor within the Intention of your Text. But you tell us, <hi>they ſay,</hi> That St. <hi>Paul means only Lawful and Rightful Kings;</hi> it is true, they do ſay ſo; but then they alſo ſay, that there are no Kings but what are Lawful or have the Legal Right, and that all others exerciſing the Kingly Power in any Kingdom, againſt Law, are onely <hi>called Kings,</hi> as Idols are <hi>called Idols,</hi> but are not true Kings. You tell us again, <hi>the Commandment is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to pray for Kings;</hi> and they ſay ſo too: but then they tell you that this doth not bind them to pray for Uſurpers, who call themſelves Kings, and are ſo called by thoſe who ſet them up againſt Law, but are not ſo. But then you think you ask them a very confounding Queſtion, though they have anſwered it an hundred times before, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Whether there is <hi>any ſuch Diſtinction as this in Scripture, that we muſt not pray for all Kings, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Legal Kings?</hi> To this they anſwer, that all Kings in the nature of the thing, and in Scripture intendment, are <hi>Legal Kings;</hi> as all Husbands and Wives, in the ſenſe of the Scriptures, are Husbands and Wives by <hi>lawful Wedlock:</hi> though an Adulterer may ſometimes uſurp the Name of a Husband, as did the pretended Husband of the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman, whom our Saviour told her for that reaſon was not her Husband. And as the Duty of Wives to their Husbands, commanded by the Apoſtle, is in no danger, by aſſerting that they muſt not be ſubject to any but Rightful Husbands: So neither, to anſwer your trifling Queſtion, <hi>are Subjects in any danger of being delivered from the Duty, in your Text, of praying for Kings,</hi> by teaching that we muſt pray for none but lawful Kings. But then you tell us, that this diſtinction of lawful Kings, from Kings that are not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <note n="*" place="margin">p. 17.</note> is Arbitrary, and that it hath no <note n="†" place="margin">p. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſolid Foundation in Reaſon and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> but they have told you over and over, that it is a Real and no Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſtinction, founded upon the common Notions of <hi>Right and Wrong, Truth and Falſhood;</hi> and that it is a diſtinction not of a thing from it ſelf (which is Arbitrary) but of a thing from what it is not; and that it is as neceſſary for Subjects to make this diſtinction between Kings, as for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Wives to diſtinguiſh betwixt lawful and unlawful Husbands and Fathers; or Clergy-men to diſtinguiſh between Canonical and Uncanonical Biſhops; or to diſtinguiſh in Religion between the true God and Idols, who
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66038:23"/> are worſhipped in the ſtile of Gods. And therefore to come to your <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia,</hi> to which you fooliſhly compare this diſtinction,<note place="margin">p. 1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they return it upon you, and ſay, that the Scriptures appropriate the Allegiance of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, of which praying is a part, to lawful Kings; but that you are more than a Papiſt in Politicks, becauſe you are for giving away not only <hi>Dulia,</hi> or half Allegiance, but <hi>Latria,</hi> or the whole Allegiance,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> from <hi>True</hi> to <hi>Idol-Kings.</hi> And then as for <hi>avoiding the Duty of the Fifth Commandment by the Vow Corban,</hi> which you miſapply to them, that returns upon your ſelf: for they have ſhew'd you again and again, in their Anſwers, that that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment directs the Duty of it to true and lawful both natural and civil Parents, and have made it appear that you are one of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who have endeavoured to make that and other Commandments of none effect, by giving the Name of Kings to pure Providential Uſurpers, though they are no more Kings by poſſeſſing the lawful Kings Throne, than Idols are Gods, by poſſeſſing the Temple of the true God. Idols have all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Divinity, as you ſay the other have of Majeſty, and by God's own Providence come to be inveſted with all the Religious Rights and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the true God, and often happen to be worſhipped and recognized for Gods by the People and Eſtates of Idolatrous Realms; but for all that they are but abominable Idols, that ought to be thrown down, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces; and the more curſed and abominable by how much the more their Worſhip is like of that of the true God. But you tell us,<note place="margin">p. 18.</note> that <hi>there is Reaſon to conclude that St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſpoke of ſuch Kings, [i. e.</hi> of Kings that were ſet up by the Eſtates and People, without legal Title,] <hi>if we will allow that he ſpoke the language of the Age wherein he lived.</hi> To which I anſwer, That neither the Language of that Age, nor any Age before or ſince the Apoſtle wrote, ever meant <hi>ſuch Kings,</hi> whenever they ſpoke of Subjects duty in Praying for Kings; and that when the Apoſtle wrote, the <hi>Roman</hi> Powers, or King or Emperour then in being, was a Lawful as well as a Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial King; and that therefore he is to be underſtood onely of lawful Kings.<note place="margin">p. 20.</note> But you on the contrary aſſert, That <hi>he wrote in a time of moſt violent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, when he had reaſon to diſtinguiſh between lawful Kings, and ſuch as were not lawful;</hi> but no Man of leſs Forehead and Conſcience than your ſelf would have aſſerted, it after the contrary had been ſo fully proved againſt you: Indeed, had the Emperor, when the Apoſtle wrote, been an Uſurper, you had ſaid ſomething to purpoſe; but this you cannot prove, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you only ſay it: But had it been true, you might eaſily have proved it, by ſhewing who was the claiming injured Party, and to whom the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire belonged by Law, and whoſe Right that unlawful Emperor did uſurp. No body will deny but that the Apoſtle wrote his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> in the Reigns of <hi>Caligula, Claudius</hi> or <hi>Nero.</hi> But to paſs over the <hi>Roman Hiſtorians,</hi> to which your Anſwerers appeal to prove they were no Uſurpers, I will here prove from the <hi>Roman Coins</hi> that they were lawful Princes, upon whom the Senate and People of the Common-Wealth of <hi>Rome</hi> had conferred the Sovereign Authority, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ſignifies Right as well as Power. Now to prove this I muſt adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66038:24"/> you, if you did not know it before, that all Coines in which we find <note n="†" place="margin">Suppetunt plane quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima ut hae literae <hi>S. C.</hi> quae in Aereis Nummis Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; in Argentis nonnullis leguntur <hi>E. X S C.</hi> quae Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tûs Conſulti Auctoritate Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos ſignificant. <hi>Anton Auguſt. Dialog. 1.</hi>
               </note> S. C. or EXS. C. as alſo S. P. Q. R. ſhew that they were coined by the ſpecial Order, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Senate: And as to their Inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions and Deviſes, were not left to Diſcretion of <hi>Triumviri monetales,</hi> or Maſters of the Mint. Therefore all ſuch Coines, as learned Medalliſts obſerve, are of greater Authority than any <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Hiſtorians,</hi> as being ſo many Publick Acts of the Senate, by which they gave as well as declared the Powers which are read in the Inſcriptions of ſuch Coines. I will begin with <hi>Caligula,</hi> of whom there are many ſuch <hi>Senatarian</hi> Coines, which on the Front or ℞ of them have S. C. or EXS. C. or S. P. Q. R. with all his Sovereign Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Titles. Of the former ſort are theſe, which about his Head bear the following Inſcriptions, CAIUS CAESAR AUG. GERMANICUS PON. MAX. TR. P. S. C. and CAIUS CAESAR DIVI AUG. PRON. AUG. P. M. TR. POT. III. P. P. S. C. Of the latter ſort are thoſe which have the foreſaid Titles on the Front, and S. C. or S. P. Q. R on the ℞℞. as that which within an oken Crown, or <hi>Corona Civica,</hi> hath inſcribed S. P. Q. R. P. P. ob. C. S. So that hath S. C. on the ℞ in which are ſtamped the Heads of his three Siſters, <hi>Agripina, Druſilla,</hi> and <hi>Livia.</hi> The ℞ of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bearing the former Titles hath the Temple which he dedicated to <hi>Anguſtus,</hi> with S. on one ſide of it, and C. on the other. And there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther curious piece extant, which hath the Head of <hi>Agripina</hi> ſurrounded with this Inſcription AGRIPPINAM. F. MAT. C. CAESARIS AUG. and on the Reverſe a <hi>Tenſa</hi> drawn by two Mules, and this Inſcription, S. P. Q. R. ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORIAE AGRIPPINAE.</p>
            <p>Then for <hi>Claudius</hi> there is a Coin which hath this Inſcription about his Head, TI. CLAUDIUS. CAESAR AUG GERM. P. M. TR. P. IMP. P. P. S. C. Another hath this Inſcription about his Image, TI. CLAUDIUS CAESAR. AUG. and on ℞ P. M. TR. P. IMP. COS. II. S. C. Another hath this Inſcription about his Image, T. CLAUDIUS CAESAR AUG. P. M. TR. P. IMP. P. P. and on ℞ SPES AUGUSTA. S. C. Another about the Head of his Mother hath ANTONIA AUGUSTA and on ℞ TITUS CLAU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIUS CAESAR AUG. P. M. S. C. On the ℞ of another bearing his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Titles, there is within an Oken Crown EXSC. OB CIVES SERVATOS. On ℞ of another, within an Oken Crown, S. P. Q. R. P. P. OB C. S Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ℞ hath CONSTANTINE AUGUSTI S.C. Another SPES AUGUSTA S. C. And another ℞. in which is ſtamped the Emperor and the Praetorian Signifer PRAETOR RECEPT. S. C.</p>
            <p>Laſtly for <hi>Nero.</hi> There is one with an Oken Crown bearing this Inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption about it, NERONI CLAUD. DIVI. F. CAES AUG. GERM. IMP. TR P. and within it EX. S. C and on ℞ AGRIPPINA AUG. DIVI. CLAUD. NERONIS. CAES. MAT. about the Heads of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Agrippina,</hi> looking one upon another. Another with <hi>Nero</hi> CLAUD. CAES. AUG. GERM. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and on the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Another hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66038:24"/> NERO CAES. AUG. IMP. about his Image, and on ℞ PONT. MAX. TR P. about an Oken Crown, and in it E X. S. C. And as for the ℞℞ on this Emperour's Coines, one hath PONTIF. MAX. TR. P. V. P. P. E X. S. C. another hath PONTIF. MAX. TR. P. VII. COS. IIII. P. P! E X. S. C. Another PONTIF. MAX. TR. P. X. COS. IIII. P. P. EX. S. C. Another a <hi>Pomana Armata,</hi> with a <hi>Victoriola</hi> on her hand, E X. S. C. Another under a triumphant Arch SC. And theſe Coins prove as plainly that theſe Emperours were lawful and rightful Emperors, as that of <hi>Pompey</hi> proves him to have been the lawful Admiral of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath this Inſcription, POMPEIUS MAGNUS PRAEFECT. CLAS. ET ORAE MARITIMAE, which Office he bore, as Hiſtorians ſhew us, in the Piratical War. And now, Doctor, as I have ſhewn from theſe Coins, that that Emperor, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was, under whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote, was a lawful Emperor, or right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Poſſeſſor of the Emperial Power; ſo let me ask you one Queſtion: is it needful that I ſhould diſtinguiſh here betwixt true and counterfeit Coins, or not? If not, then it was much leſs needful for the Apoſtle to diſtinguiſh between <hi>lawful Kings</hi> and Kings that were not lawful, becauſe he wrote under a lawful King, that had no Competitor at home or abroad to claim or proſecute his Right againſt him: But becauſe there are many Cavans or counterfeit Coins, I here diſtinguiſh between them, though I think I need not, and tell you, that I have made uſe of none but true Coins: But if you ſuſpect me, you may borrow a litte from the Bp. of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> as you did a little <note n="*" place="margin">See the learned Anſwer to the Biſhop, <hi>aaa.</hi>
               </note> Chronology about <hi>Jaddus</hi> from him, and he'll help you out in both alike. And in the mean time, Doctor, take this with you, That your <hi>pure Providential</hi> King in Policy, are no better than counterfeit Medals in Antiquity, or <hi>Briſtol</hi>-ſtones among Diamonds; they ſhew and gliſter like Kings, but are not Kings, but Uſurpers: And the diſtinction between them and Kings, by the help of the Word <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful,</hi> is as real and natural as that of the Nummiſts between real and forged Medals, or that of the Jewellers between true and falſe Diamonds, or that of all the World between true and counterfeit Silver and Gold. It is the Appearance of Things without Reality that is the Ground of this diſtinction; and to diſcover real from apparent, true from falſe, and right from wrong in the moral and natural World, makes theſe diſtinctions uſeful, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would be uſeleſs; and when Authors do not uſe them in ſpeaking of Things, they are ſuppoſed to ſpeak of <hi>real, true,</hi> and right things of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kind, and not of things of another Nature, that for ſome ſhew, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or falſe Pretenſions, are called by their Names. You think you ſpeak finely, when you ſay it is matter of <hi>Senſe</hi> to know who is King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Man may ſee who adminiſters the Government by Regal Authority. But if it be matter of Senſe, Doctor, how came you to loſe your Senſes ſo long? And what made you ſo blind that you could not ſee it when other Men did? This ſhews, Doctor, that it is not matter of <hi>Senſe,</hi> but of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> for Senſe can onely perceive the ſupream external Force that is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in any Kingdom; but to diſcern the Right or Authority to exerciſe the ſupreme Force of Power which makes a King; is the work of Reaſon; becauſe Authority is a <hi>moral Quality,</hi> as hath been <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> ch. 20.</note> excellently proved to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66038:25"/> you, of which Reaſon and Conſcience is Judge. O but then, ſay you, it muſt be a <hi>matter of Wit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>or Law, or Philoſophy, to know who is King.</hi> It is ſo, Doctor; but of no more Wit, Law, and Philoſophy, than every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Underſtanding hath; and no more than is needful to know who is Husband,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Entituled,</hi> The Reſurrection of Loyalty and Obedience out of the Grave of Rebellion, by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Force of the Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance. <hi>Printed for</hi> Will. Shears <hi>in</hi> Bedford-<hi>ſtreet near</hi> Covent-Garden, <hi>at the blue Bible, and inſcribed</hi> to Gen. Monk.</note> or Maſter of any Family, or Parſon of any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or Mayor of any Corporation. <hi>The World knows</hi> (ſaith an excellent little Book) <hi>who it is that the Law and Cuſtome of this Nation ſtates to be the Heir and Succeſſor of the King, even the eldeſt Son of the Predeceſſor.</hi> In truth, Doctor, there is no difficulty in it; there is not a Countrey Fellow in any Kingdom but knows by what Title the Crown is held; and in an hereditary Kingdom there is no great need of Wit, or Law, or Philoſophy, to know the Royal Family, and the next Heir in it. But you have had enough of this in your learned Anſwerers; and none but a Man that is deſperate, and paſt bluſhing, would preach the ſame Stuff again,<note place="margin">P. 19.</note> eſpecially before ſuch an Audience, when he knew he could not defend what he ſaid. But you tell us, <hi>you will not diſpute the Matter;</hi> and the Reaſon is plain, becauſe you cannot diſpute it, though you are one of the Diſputers of this World, your Adverſaries having put the Controverſie beyond all reaſonable Diſpute. But if you will not diſpute it, why ſhould you meddle any more with it? Or is it becauſe you are a great Man, and a great <hi>Rabbi,</hi> that ought not to diſpute with ſuch <hi>little Writers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. Well; but though you will not diſpute them, yet you'l vouchſafe to chatechiſe them,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and ask them ſome hard Queſtions about <hi>Certainty:</hi> And before I anſwer for them, I muſt beg leave, Doctor, tho' of late you do not love diſtinctions, to diſtinguiſh about <hi>Certainty,</hi> and I hope it is no <hi>arbitrary diſtinction, that hath no Foundation in Reaſon and Nature. Certainty</hi> then, Doctor, is of two ſorts, <hi>abſolute,</hi> of which no doubt can poſſibly be made, and againſt which there lies no Objection; or <hi>ſuch,</hi> which though it be not free from all doubts and Objections; yet it is ſuch as the nature of the Thing will bear, and ſuch as command a firm aſſent of the Mind, without doubting of the truth of what it believes. The firſt is a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical or Metaphyſical Certainty, and with this abſolute, mathematical, and metaphyſical Certainty, you, and I, and all the World, are ſure that <hi>two and two make four,</hi> and that <hi>a thing cannot be and not be at the ſame time.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>moral Certainty,</hi> which reſults from Reaſons on one ſide in every Matter and Queſtion, that viſibly preponderate the Reaſons on the other, and ſo commands the Aſſent of a Man's Underſtanding, that he hath either no doubt, or very weak ones, of the truth of the thing which he believes. This indeed is a ſort of Certainty inferior to the other; but yet ſuch a one as you, and I, and all Men, have of moſt of the things of which we are certain, as that there was ſuch a Man as <hi>Moſes;</hi> and upon this ſort of Certainty, and no other, we make no doubt of venturing our Lives and Eſtates in this World, and our Souls in the next. I preſume, Doctor, you will allow this for a good diſtinction; and if you do, then, with ſubmiſſion, I muſt ask you, Which Certainty do you mean in the Queſtions you have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66038:25"/> put to <hi>theſe Men.</hi> I dare ſay you do not mean the former, for ſome ill Conſequences I need not mention; but if the latter, then Dr. for once permit one of the <hi>little Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to ſhew you the Folly and Vanity of this way of arguing in Queſtions about <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty,</hi> from a few Queſtions of the ſame Nature. Are you certain then, that your Text is the Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or that they were written by divine Inſpiration? Are you certain that there are there Perſons in the holy Trinity? That there is ſuch a Continent as <hi>America?</hi> Or, to jeſt and argue together, are you certain that your Prieſts Orders are valid, that your Marriage with your incomparable Lady was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or that your Children are your own? The anſwering theſe Queſtions, Dr. will help to convince you, to what little purpoſe you put ſo many of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture about Certainty; however I will anſwer them in order.</p>
            <p>To the firſt then, <hi>they ſay,</hi> that they are as certain that by all Powers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. the Apoſtle only means ſuch as have legal Right and Title to Power, as they are that he expreſly teaches, that <hi>all Power is of God.</hi> But, 2. They alſo ſay, that tho' they were not ſo certain, which is not neceſſary; yet they are ſo certain of it, as that they make no doubt of it, and venture <hi>their All,</hi> here and hereafter, upon the truth of it. Your ſecond Queſtion, <hi>they ſay,</hi> agrees not with your firſt, nor with the deſign of your Sermon: For when you ask them whether they are as certain that it is <hi>unlawful</hi> to pray for Kings <hi>legally inveſted,</hi> &amp;c. as they are that the Apoſtle commands us to pray for Kings; they ſay, that according to your <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> the queſtoin ought to be put of Kings <hi>illegally inveſted</hi> with the <hi>Royal Power;</hi> and then they anſwer, that illegal Kings cannot be legally inveſted, and as certain that it is as <hi>unlawful</hi> to pray for illegal Kings, as they are that the Apoſtle commands us to pray <hi>for Kings, and all that are in Authority;</hi> and likewiſe add, as before to the Anſwer of the firſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. In your third <hi>they obſerve,</hi> that you call the <hi>lawful</hi> King's Right a <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> Right, whereas the <hi>providential</hi> King's Right is <hi>merely ſo;</hi> but the <hi>lawful</hi> King out of Poſſeſſion hath, according to your ſtate of the Controverſie, a <hi>real</hi> Right to poſſeſs, and to recover Poſſeſſion if he can; and therefore if they could wonder at you for any thing, they ſay they ſhould wonder why you call it a <hi>ſuppoſed Right:</hi> And in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to anſwer the queſtion, as they are a diſtinguiſhing ſort of Men; ſo they diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh about <hi>Eſtates of the Realm,</hi> and <hi>they ſay</hi> they are of three ſorts: 1. Eſtates that are always free. 2. Eſtates that are ſometimes free. And, 3. Eſtates that are never free. The firſt are Sovereign Eſtates, as the Eſtates of <hi>Rome</hi> formerly were, and thoſe of <hi>Venice</hi> now are, in whom the ſupreme Authority is lodged, and all Perſons in their Dominions are ſubject to them, and they are ſubject unto none. The ſecond are the Eſtates of Elective Kingdoms, where there is an <hi>Interregnum</hi> of Freedom to chuſe a new King in, as in <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſome other Kingdoms. And the third are the Eſtates of Hereditary Kingdoms, where by Law there is no <hi>Interreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> but the laſt moment of one King's Reign is the firſt of another, and where by conſequence all Ranks and Orders of Men are conſtantly ſubject, even as conſtantly as if they had but one immortal, or never dying King. This diſtinction being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, they anſwer <hi>in Theſi,</hi> that they are certain that it is the Duty of Subjects to adhere to the legal Right, and him that hath it, in oppoſition to an unlawful King, put into the Throne by ſubject and unfree Eſtates, that have no Authority, Right, or Liberty to make Kings, becauſe the Law hath always Kings ready made for them, to whom they ought to be ſubject. I ſay they are certain, nay as certain that it is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66038:26"/> the Duty of Subjects, whatever they ſuffer by it, to adhere to the legal Right in ſuch a Caſe, as they are that it is our duty to pray for Kings. And then to your laſt Queſtion they anſwer, that they are <hi>as certain</hi> that the <hi>Roman</hi> Powers or Emperors were legal and rightful Powers, when the Apoſtle wrote, <hi>as</hi> that he commanded the Chriſtians to be ſubject to them, and pray for them: For they were placed in the Throne by free Eſtates, who had Authority to place them there; but you, more like a Sophiſter than a Preacher of Truth, take no notice of this plane diſtinction, as if the Eſtates of all Kingdoms were alike free and Sovereign: <hi>Theſe Men,</hi> ſay you, (p. 18.) <hi>will pray for no Kings unleſs they be legal Kings, tho' they have all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Majeſty, and are inveſted with the legal Authority and Power, with all the legal and cuſtomary Rights and Solemnities of Inveſtiture, and are acknowledged and recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm.</hi> Theſe are fine words, Dr. but did you never hear of Realms where Kings are Kings without any Enſigns of Majeſty, before the Solemnitie of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation; of Realms where the King, <hi>quatenus</hi> King, never dyeth, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence where the Eſtates are always ſubject to the King, and have no <hi>Interregnum</hi> of Freedom; of Realms where for the aforeſaid Reaſon the King is ſaid to demiſe when he departs this Life, and where the King is crowned becauſe he is King, and not King becauſe he is crowned? Fie, Dr. fie; I am aſhamed of your Ignorance, if you have lived among Lawyers ſo long, and not know theſe things, or of ſomething worſe than that, if you knew them, and ſuppreſs them becauſe they did not ſuit with you Providential Scheme.</p>
            <p>I have now, Dr. anſwered your Queſtions plainly, and perhaps more plainly than you deſired; but to ſhew you and the <hi>Worſhipful Bench</hi> how much you dare impoſe upon them, I muſt ask you the ſame queſtions, the ſame <hi>proper queſtions about degrees of Evidence</hi> and Certitude, (p. 20.) Come therefore, Dr. ſublime, ſeraphick, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable Dr. for once vouchſafe to anſwer a poor <hi>little Writer,</hi> who humbly deſires to know, 1. Whether you are as certain, that by all Powers <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle means Powers that have no legal Right and Title, as well as Powers that have legal Right and Title and proſecute that Right, as you are that he expreſly teaches <hi>that all Power is of God?</hi> 2. Whether you are as certain that it is lawful to pray for <hi>unlawful Kings,</hi> who have no legal Right to the Power which they exerciſe, as you are that the Apoſtle commands us to pray <hi>for Kings, and all that are in Authority?</hi> 3. Whether you are as certain that it is the Subjects duty to adhere to a ſuppoſed Providential Right, againſt the Laws of the Realm, and in oppoſition to the <hi>lawful King,</hi> and his Right, as you are that it is our duty to pray <hi>for Kings?</hi> 4. Are you as certain that the <hi>Roman</hi> Powers, when the Apoſtles wrote, were illegal and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Powers, which you affirm, as you are that St. <hi>Paul</hi> commanded Chriſtians <hi>to be ſubject to them, and to pray for them?</hi> Theſe, Dr. are your own Queſtions, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you can anſwer them better than any other Man; but when you think fit to do ſo, let me entreat you not to perplex the Controverſie of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>legal Right,</hi> with the Word <hi>antecedent,</hi> as you have done in your Sermon 4 or 5 times, merely to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muze your Readers, and fill them with Prejudice againſt <hi>theſe Men;</hi> as if they would own no Man for King, but ſuch as comes to the Adminiſtration of the Sovereign Power with an <hi>antecedent Right.</hi> But this, Dr. is a great, and I fear a wilful miſtake of yours; for provided that he that hath the actual Adminiſtration of Government hath a legal Right to it, it is all one to them whether it be an <hi>antecedent, concomitant,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:66038:26"/> or <hi>conſequent Right; Right,</hi> or <hi>legal Right</hi> is the thing that they look after in him that hath the Sovereign Power, and that alone which can lay the Obligation of Obedience upon Men's Conſciences, and command Subjection from them. Sovereign Power, how providentially ſoever it is attained, is but Sovereign Force and Tyranny with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and to ſpeak in logical Strictneſs, <hi>King</hi> is a name of Law and <hi>Right;</hi> and aſſoon as a Man hath the Right which the Law gives to Sovereign Power, he is King; and King no ſooner than he hath that <hi>Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now anſwered every thing in your Sermon relating to the Controverſie concerning Kings, and I here declare that I have onely defended the Principles and Reaſonings of your Adverſaries againſt you; but if they be miſtaken in Law, and miſapply them and this to the wrong <hi>Object,</hi> let them anſwer themſelves for their Miſtake. My deſign and buſineſs is only to reſcue your Text, and that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and the Duties there commanded, from the mere <hi>Providential</hi> to the <hi>Legal King;</hi> but if thoſe Men have ſo little <hi>Wit, Law,</hi> or <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> nay, ſo little common Senſe, as of two Pretenders to the Crown at any time, not to know which hath the legal Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, their Miſtake may prove fatal, but I have nothing to doe with that. I am ſure, Dr. you have done <hi>their Majeſties</hi> much Diſſervice by awarding the legal Right from them, and giving them inſtead of it, <hi>an airy Title by Providence,</hi> which <hi>Athaliah, Abſolom,</hi> and <hi>Cromwel</hi> had, and every proſperous Uſurper can pretend to and I am confident had they been rightly informed of the nature of your Principle; and of that looſe and fickle, and worthleſs Allegiance which Princes only get by it, they would have had your <hi>Caſe of Allegiance</hi> cenſured, as it deſerves, and inſtead of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring you, had puniſhed you as the underminer of their Throne. I am certain had you wrote and preached ſo in any of the former Proteſtant Raigns, you would have been ſeverely cenſured, and puniſhed by the Laws of Church and State; and if, as you tell us, the Revolution hath made no Alteration in Government, it is not yet too late to bring you to condign Puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="15">15. I thought I ſhould have made an end, but finding ſome other Paſſages in your Sermon, upon which the Reader may expect I ſhould make ſome Reflections. I cannot well paſs them over. Firſt then I cannot but animadvert upon the great and undecent Liberty you take of ſpeaking of the <hi>FRENCH KING,</hi> in this, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all your Sermons; whereas in <hi>France</hi> that Antichriſtian Tyrant, as you mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly call him, will not ſuffer the greateſt of his Clergy to bring ſo much as a <hi>rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Accuſation</hi> againſt their Majeſties, or meddle with their Adminiſtration, as you, and the Bp. of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and I know not how many more, preſume to do with his. But who made you Judges over him? He is God's Miniſter, and God's annointed Servant, and <hi>who art thou that judgeſt another Man's Servant? To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> And what have you to doe to impeach him of Tyranny, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Oppreſſion? Do you know the reaſons of his Actions, or can you tell what may be ſaid to juſtifie or excuſe the worſt thing that he ever did? You told Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rnet</hi> at <hi>Ely-houſe,</hi> when he ſpoke reproachfully of <hi>King James,</hi> that <hi>Crowned Heads ought not to be ſo treated;</hi> but now, Dr. you make no difficulty of treating the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Crowned Heads at a much worſe rate, tho' he is God's ordinance on a double account, both as a Legal and Providential King. One would think, to read in what a loſty and inſolent manner you ſpeak of him, that you were your ſelf <hi>IMP. PON. MAX.</hi> or ſome <hi>great Prophet,</hi> that had received Commiſſion from Heaven to arraign Kings. Certainly there is ſomething very extraordinary in you, ſomething very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66038:27"/> or very diabolical, that of late you have a Mouth given you ſpeaking Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt Kings, and againſt a King who has as many and great Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues as any King in the World, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>f. ſ.</hi> p. 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Perſecutor, Oppreſſor, Enſlaver of Mens Bodies and Souls, Tyrant,</hi> and <hi>antichriſtian Tyrant.</hi> This, Dr. ſounds like the <hi>Language of the Beaſt,</hi> not of a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> it runs in the Style of an Excommunication Bull; and as you are as great as the Pope in your own Opinion, ſo you have learnt to huff and hector Kings: But, what! are you thus to take upon you? You who but the other day were digging in <hi>Gravel-lane</hi> for Bread, to what an height are you come from almoſt nothing, and a Conventicle, to defie Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Heads! But we know from whence all this comes, even from a moſt ſervile Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that cares not what it ſaith or doth, ſo it humor the Times, and pleaſe the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Of this <hi>no</hi> man hath been more guilty than you, and I will give you and the World an inſtance of it. Sometimes Liberty and Indulgence to Diſſenters were in vogue, and ſometimes not; and accordingly you watcht the Opportunities, and wrote <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> on it on both ſides: You were for it in your Preface to your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Aſſemblies,</hi> and you were againſt it in your Anſwer to <hi>Whitby,</hi> and your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon the Plot;</hi> but for it again in your Sermon before the Ld. Mayor, a little before the Revolution; and I doubt not but another <hi>Criſis</hi> would make you once more againſt it. From this <hi>Time-ſerving</hi> and <hi>Self-ſeeking Principle</hi> it comes, that the <hi>French K.</hi> is made the common place of Satyr in your and other ſuch Clergy-mens Sermons. He hath taken the part of <hi>K. James,</hi> and that makes him ſo great a Tyrant; but had he been againſt him, and the Confederate Power for him, then they had been the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Oppreſſors; and he that is now a <hi>Nero,</hi> a <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> had then been a moſt excellent <hi>Prince.</hi> How many Declamations had Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> by this time made for him, and againſt them, if he had been our Allie, and his victorious Legions employed in our Service? Then we had heard again from the Pulpits the old <hi>Philippicks</hi> againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Inquiſition;</hi> the Pulpits would have rung then with <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and the <hi>Hungarian Perſecutions;</hi> and we ſhould have been told again of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and all the <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Inſults</hi> of the <hi>Dutch:</hi> But as the Caſe now ſtands, nothing muſt be ſaid againſt them; the <hi>French K.</hi> is the only <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and all the <hi>Tyrants</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> a very <hi>Devil</hi> in humane ſhape. Well, Dr. you know many men have made Speeches in praiſe of the <hi>Plague,</hi> and <hi>Famine,</hi> and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for once let us defend a <hi>Paradox,</hi> and try what may be ſaid for <hi>Buſiris,</hi> or rather for the <hi>Hercules</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> You tell us <hi>he invades the Liberties of</hi> Europe; but I proteſt that is News to me, for I never heard before that he made War with <hi>Europe. Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Denmark, Poland, Switzerland, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> as I take it, are all in <hi>Europe;</hi> but I hear them not complain of him for uſurping on their Liberties, or pretend to have any <hi>Repriſals</hi> to make upon him. Beſides, Dr. I am not able to underſtand <hi>what are the Liberties of</hi> Europe, and deſire to know where they are, or in what <hi>Code</hi> or <hi>Charter</hi> one may find them. If <hi>Europe</hi> have any Liberties, it muſt be a Community; but I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read of the Community of <hi>Europe,</hi> tho' I have of that of <hi>Aſia,</hi> (which was a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity</hi> of 13 Cities in the <hi>Proconſular Aſia,</hi>) both in <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Coins.</hi> The Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Aſia</hi> coined a fine new Medal to the memory of <hi>Germanicus</hi> and <hi>Druſus,</hi> which on the Reverſe within a Lawrel Crown hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and they alſo coined Medals in memory of a Temple which they conſecrated to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66038:27"/> COM on one ſide of the Temple, and ASIAE on the other; but I never read of any thing done by the <hi>Community</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and would be glad to be informed what the Nature and Conſtitution of it is, where it holds its <hi>Dyets,</hi> when it chuſes the <hi>Europarcha,</hi> and in what place its Members or their Deputies meet: But it may be, Doctor, by the Liberties of <hi>Europe</hi> you mean thoſe of the <hi>Confederate Part</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> and if you do, then, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting our own Countrey, I pray tell me where the People live better, or enjoy greater Liberties than they do in <hi>France.</hi> In <hi>France</hi> truly the common People go in wooden Shoes, and in moſt of the foreign Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Countries they have the Liberty to go barefoot; in <hi>France</hi> they have whole <hi>Canvaſs,</hi> or other <hi>mean Cloathing,</hi> and in many of the <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Countries</hi> they are half naked; and if indeed King <hi>Lewis</hi> were ſuch an <hi>Oppreſſour of Liberties,</hi> then the Common People, and Burghors, and Clergy of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> would not ſo favour him, and deſire to come under <hi>his Government,</hi> as we are informed they do: The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Clergy underhand commend him to their People, and the Clergy and learned men of his own Kingdom admire him; and this ſhews at leaſt that he is good to the Clergy, and maintains their Privileges and Revenues; and that, Doctour, I tell you is <hi>maintaining our Religion</hi> in their Style as well as <hi>ours.</hi> You blame him alſo for <hi>deſtroying and extirpating his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects;</hi> but would you blame him if he did it becauſe they had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to <hi>deſtroy and extirpate</hi> him? You formerly ſaid in one of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that <hi>If the Conſciences of Subjects will ſerve them to rebell for Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reflexions on the Diſcovery of the late Plot, p. 15.</note> 
               <hi>it ſeems a very hard Caſe, if the Conſcience of the Prince muſt not allow him to hang them for their Rebellion.</hi> And ſo, Sir, if the Conſciences of Subjects will ſerve them to <hi>extirpate</hi> their <hi>King;</hi> it is very hard, if he comes to the knowledge of it, that he may not be beforehand with them, and <hi>extirpate them.</hi> The <hi>French King</hi> is no ſtranger to the <hi>Civil Wars</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> he knew what <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> had been the cauſe of moſt of them; and as ſenſible as he is of his own <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> yet he knew he was not a Match to <hi>Confederate Enemies</hi> without, and <hi>Rebels</hi> within, at the ſame time: Wherefore he thought it for the ſafety of his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> to ſend the Trumpeters of Rebellion betimes out of his Kingdom, who ſince have ſollicited all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> againſt him, and plainly ſhewn, that if <hi>they</hi> did not know what Spirit they were of, <hi>he</hi> did. I muſt here beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, O ye humble and holy Souls of <hi>Ramus, Charpenter, Moulin, Amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rault,</hi> and <hi>Bouchart!</hi> You indeed were not fighting Evangeliſts; but there were few ſuch as you in times paſt, and fewer of late among the <hi>French Proteſtants,</hi> who would prefer the <hi>Croſs</hi> before the <hi>Sword.</hi> The Attempt and Actions of ſome of them this Summer have juſtified their King, and diſcovered the Secret of his Severity againſt them, as Monſieur <hi>Louvois</hi> did ſome time ſince to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lord, to whom he appointed a time on purpoſe to diſcourſe on that Subject, and then aſſured him that his Maſter had diſcovered a dangerous Correſpondence betwixt his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and that to prevent the ill Conſequences of it, had once clapt up a haſty Peace with them, and found he could not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66038:28"/> be ſafe in the next War, whenever that ſhould happen, unleſs he firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued them. The Converſation we have had with them doth confirm this Opinion of their King; they are generally known to be for the curſed Doctrine of Reſiſtence; and for my part I never heard but of <note n="*" place="margin">The Author of a Book, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Traite du Pourvoir abſolu des Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Soveraines,</hi> &amp;c.</note> one of them that was againſt it: The reſt openly avow it, as <hi>Jurieux</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Allix</hi> now Canon of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who although he had begg'd leave of King <hi>James</hi> to dedicate a <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Title of the Book is,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexious ſur les Cinque Livres de Moyſe. <hi>It was printed at</hi> London, <hi>1687 But the Dedication of it bears date</hi> Dec. <hi>12. 1636. In that he declares, that</hi> the Favours which his Majeſty had done to th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of their Nation, who ſought for Repoſe under the ſhadow of his Scepter, were ſo <hi>great,</hi> and the Manner in which his Majeſty had ſignalized his Compaſſion towards them, had had ſuch Effect on the Spirits of his Subjects, that all the World ought to <hi>abhor them,</hi> if they had not a lively ſenſe of his Benefits, and did not endeavour to ſignaliz<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Eternal Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to him. <hi>Then he proceeds to make a ſolemn</hi> Proteſtation <hi>in his own name, and the name of his ſuffering Countreymen,</hi> of a profound Submiſſion to his Majeſty's Commands, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable fidelity to his Service; <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that he was the</hi> greateſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God had choſen to protect and comfort <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their Miſeries, and that it was to God that they applied themſelves in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual Obligations of moſt ardent Vows for his Proſperity: <hi>And in the Concluſion begs leave that his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would accept the</hi> weak Efforts of his Zeal, and permit him to ſtyle himſelf his Majeſty's moſt humble and moſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Subiect and Servant, <hi>P. Allix. But forgetting all this when the Biſhops were in the Tower, he ſaid to one of his Acquaintance,</hi> What do the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Lords mean? Why do they not fly to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</note> Book to him, in token of his Gratitude, and the Gratitude of his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for the Protection and the Kindneſs they had received from him; yet upon the Revolution he did all he could to ſuppreſs the <hi>Dedication</hi> in which he had ſet forth his Majeſty's Praiſes, and railed againſt him in his diſtreſs with all the Rage that a Tongue could do that was ſet on fire of Hell. That King was not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their Spirit, no more than their own; for when the Biſhops interceded with his Majeſty for a <hi>Brief</hi> in their Behalf, <hi>My Lords,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Perhaps if you know theſe Men as well as I, you would not ask this of me; but you ſhall ſee I am a Chriſtian, and that I can doe good to them that hate me. Theſe Men I know are mine Enemies; but nevertheleſs I will not onely grant them a</hi> Brief, <hi>that my People may relieve them, but I will alſo relieve them my ſelf.</hi> And as he foretold it came to paſs; for they liſted in great numbers againſt him, and help'd to drive him out of his Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> although, Doctour, he had your Title of Providence to it, and was recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm. This, Doctour, I fear is the Spirit, and theſe the Principles, generally ſpeaking, of the <hi>Refugees;</hi> and this Spirit, and theſe Principles, of which they give ſo many Signs, obliged the King for his own Security to ſend their Miniſters out of his Kingdom; but he did not ſend them away empty, he did not ſend them to the Galleys, as you know who did. What I have ſaid, Doctour, is out of juſtice, and not out of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the <hi>French Monarch,</hi> I am none of thoſe that <hi>wiſh he may prevail, and bear all before him like a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> but I do not like that he ſhould be ignorantly and partially traduc'd by every ſoul mouth'd Pulpitier, when were it not for his invincible Miſtake in Religion, he would be thought, even by you, one of the braveſt Princes that ever wore a Crown: Nor have I any ill Will at his Proteſtant Subjects; I have been as great a Reliever of them in proportion to my Ability, as any other Man in the Kingdom, and ſhould be glad to ſee a <hi>Vindication</hi> of them, that I might have a better Opinion of them. I grant the King hath perſecuted them with very great Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66038:28"/> and made havock of their Church, and am as ſorry as you can be for it, and for the Cauſe of it; but then are there no perſecutors among the Confederate Princes? Look about you, Doctor; ſet the Acts, and Edicts, and Executions of other Princes againſt his; and then you will find, that other Proteſtants beſides the <hi>French</hi> have been <hi>dragoon'd,</hi> and loſt their Eſtates, their Lives, their Liberties, and their Countrey, for Conſcience ſake. In ſhort, the <hi>French</hi> Apologiſts tell us, that the King perſecuted them, becauſe they intended to perſecute him: This their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences can tell them whether it be true or no; and if it be true, then their deſtruction is of themſelves, and they have brought down their Ruine upon their own Heads. The Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> who foretold the Downfall of their King, hath now foretold his Converſion, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: It is ſome Months ago ſince he foretold that this would happen within a year; God grant his Prediction may prove true; it would make his Majeſty a <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to his People: But yet I fear that would not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie ſome Men, nor reconcile their ulcerated Minds to him, unleſs with the <hi>Popiſh Religion</hi> he quitted the Intereſts of King <hi>James.</hi> This, Doctor, is another <hi>crowned Head,</hi> againſt whom you love to croak: All your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Speeches and Slanders of him, and particularly thoſe in your firſt and ſecond Letter concerning the <hi>French Invaſion,</hi> are filed up in Heaven, and ſhall be brought in Evidence againſt you at the great Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, when, without publick and bitter Repentance, you will appear at the left Hand, with <hi>Cromwell, Bradſhaw, Cook, Milton,</hi> and <hi>Thom. Good. win,</hi> and be ſent with thoſe Worthies of the Old Cauſe into your own place. You cannot be content with ſober and wiſe Men among your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to ſay nothing of him; or when you ſpeak, to ſpeak of him as they do, with <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Reſpect:</hi> but you fall upon him as the Mob did at <hi>Feverſham,</hi> with a brutal Rage, without any Regard to his Royal Name and Perſon, or to her Majeſty and the Princeſs, whom you diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in reproaching of him: For let me tell you, Doctor, the <hi>Diſgrace</hi> of the <hi>Chief</hi> always terminates in the <hi>Clan;</hi> and the Men of Honour will tell you, they are bound to revenge it, as ſoon as they have the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
            <p n="16">16. In this Sermon you alſo upbraid him with his Misfortunes, which no good Man can think of, without the greateſt degree of Compaſſion, ſcornfully calling him <hi>the late unfortunate Prince.</hi> It is true, Doctor, he is <hi>unfortunate;</hi> but you ſhould have remembred what <hi>Solon</hi> ſaid of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> and that what happens to <hi>Kings</hi> may alſo happen to <hi>Divines.</hi> You live now in great Proſperity, and State; but God may yet bring you down: He can when he pleaſes take off the Wheels of your Chariot, turn your Silver Candeleſticks into Braſs, and your Wax Candles into Tallow, and reduce you even beyond your firſt principals, yet before you dye. I wiſh this may not happen to you, nor none of thoſe who inſult over the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of that <hi>unfortunate Prince;</hi> but if it do ſo, remember you ſaw the Anguiſh of his Soul, and had no Pity for him, and then ſay, <hi>therefore if this Diſtreſs come upon us,</hi>— One of the <hi>Nine Men,</hi> when he heard
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66038:29"/> him pitied, had the Barbarity to ſay, <hi>Why, what matter is it? He is but a Baſtard, St.</hi> Alban<hi>'s Baſtard;</hi> and it is great pity that her Majeſty had not been told of it, before he <hi>put on his Lawn Slieves.</hi> We commonly ſay <hi>Misfortunes are no Crimes;</hi> and before you upbraid him with them again, remember his Father, the <hi>Martyr of the Church of</hi> England, was unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate before him, and had this alſo added to the reſt of his Misfortunes, that he was reviled, and had in deriſion by ſuch Sons of the Earth as you. But God ſupported him by his Grace, and <hi>made him more than Conqueror;</hi> and the ſame God which ſupported the Father, hath alſo upheld the Son under his Misfortunes; which let me tell you, had never come upon him, had you and your Brethren the Clergy done their Duty, as ſome of them did: And therefore methinks you ſhould take no pleaſure in ripping up his Misfortunes, which are <hi>your Crimes.</hi> He was <hi>unfortunate</hi> in you more than in his Lay Subjects: You might have ſaved him, as well as your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if you would have preached but half as much for him as you did for that; but your general Silence in the needfull time betrayed him to all his Misfortunes, and Now <hi>ſuch as you</hi> among your Brethren are very ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that they are not greater, and mad againſt the <hi>ſuffering Remnant,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not renounce him in his Misfortunes, and murmur againſt God that hath preſerved him, and laid Help upon one that is mighty for him; a mighty <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath long maintain'd more Legions than the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire did at the higheſt Pitch of Greatneſs, and who perhaps one day, like <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Trajan,</hi> may inſcribe upon his Medals coined upon ſuch <hi>glorious Occaſions, REX PARTHIS REX ARMENIS DAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> for God ſeldom raiſes <hi>Princes</hi> to that Greatneſs, but he hath ſomething extraordinary for them to doe. I muſt alſo remind you of another great Bleſſing, which God, who remembers Mercy in Judgment has beſtowed upon him, and thereby enabled him the better to bear the loſs of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: He hath given him of his moſt virtuous Queen a Royal <note n="*" place="margin">See the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed <hi>Monday Aug.</hi> 21. and <hi>Wedneſday Aug.</hi> 23. 1682.</note> Son and Daughter, by whom I truſt the Royal Family will be multiplied into many Branches, and come to be reſtored to its antient Rights and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Seed of the Royal Martyr is in them; and I hope it is no Crime to pray, that God would give them the <hi>ſure Mercies of</hi> David, <hi>and let them grow up like tender Plants before him, in Wiſdom, and Stature, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour both with God and Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Another thing, Doctor, I cannot but take notice of, is your <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuical</hi> and moſt exorbitant manner of aggrandizing our late Victory at Sea, which encreaſes that Contempt the World had before of you, and hath given juſt occaſion to ſome obſerving men, who have compared your Character of it with that of the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> and Dr. <hi>Scot</hi> to affirm, that there was never ſo much Flattering heard from the <hi>Engliſh Pulpits</hi> as in theſe days.<note place="margin">In his Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Sermon before the Queen, p. 23.</note> Dr. <hi>Scot</hi> in lofty ſtrains ſaith, <hi>That it is one of the moſt glorious and ſignal Victories that ever the Sea beheld;</hi> and yet afterwards tells us how much their ſtrength was inferiour to ours. And you ſay, that <hi>no Story can equal it, except we compare it to the miraculous Overthrow of</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and all his Hoſt in the red Sea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 31.</note> I profeſs to you, <hi>Doctor,</hi> I am no great Hiſtorian;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66038:29"/> but to ſhew you much the Doctor and you ſhot above the mark, I will preſent you with a Summary of a few <hi>Sea Fights,</hi> where the Victory hath been incomparably greater than this laſt of ours.</p>
            <p>In the Battel at <hi>Salamis, Themiſtocles</hi> with CCCLXXX defeated the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Navy, conſiſting of MCCC. In the Battel between the <hi>Phalacrian</hi> Promontory and the mouth of the River <hi>Helicon</hi> in <hi>Sicily, C. Druillius</hi> with a leſſer Navy vanquiſhed the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of CXXX Sail, of which, beſides thoſe he deſtroyed, he took L, of which <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the Admiral's Ship, was one, and the greateſt part of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> were alſo ſlain. Before this, I think, <hi>Claudius Pulcher,</hi> the Conſul, fighting with an ill <hi>Omen</hi> againſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> was defeated, and of CCXX Ships he ſaved onely XXX, the Enemies having taken and ſunk the reſt, Twenty thouſand being made Captives. <hi>Attilus Regulus</hi> and <hi>Manlius Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> in another Sea Fight againſt <hi>Amilcar,</hi> took LXX Veſſels, with all their men, and ſunk LXIV. And <hi>Marcus Aemilius,</hi> and <hi>Servius Fulvius,</hi> with CCCL. Veſſels, routed the Fleet of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> in which they killed XVM men, and took and ſunk CXIV Ships. <hi>C. Lutatius Catulus,</hi> with no more than CCC Veſſels, routed the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of CCCC ſail; of which he took L, and ſunk LXX; or, as <hi>Eutropius</hi> writes, he took LXXIII, and ſunk CXXV; took 30000 Priſoners, and ſlew 13000; after which, the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> who had ſo bravely diſputed the Empire of the Sea, were forced to ſue for Peace; which I do not hear the <hi>French</hi> King hath done yet. But to take a great leap from Antient to modern Hiſtory, at the Famous Battel of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> the Chriſtians under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria, October</hi> 7. 1571. defeated the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Fleet, though double in number of Gallies to theirs; and the particular Account of this great Victory is thus in <hi>Knolls</hi>'s <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Hiſtory: They took 161 Gallies, with 60 other ſmaller Veſſels, and ſunk and burnt 40 Gallies more. The number of the ſlain was uncertain, but they were reckoned about 30000, other Accounts ſay 25000, and they delivered 1200 Slaves; and all but with the loſs of 7566 men. And within the memory of Man <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Whitlock</hi>'s Memoirs, p. 515, 516.</note> 
               <hi>Blake,</hi> in 1652, with 8 Fregats fought 12 <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, ſunk 3, and took the reſt. <note n="†" place="margin">p. 532.</note> 
               <hi>June</hi> 1653. the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> without the loſs of one Ship, and but with the loſs of 126 men, beſides General <hi>Dean,</hi> and one Captain, took 20 <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, 1350 Priſoners, and their whole loſs amounted, by their own computation, to 5000 men; among the Ships that were taken were one Viceadmiral, and two Rearadmirals. <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 1ſt, 1653. in a ſharp Fight between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> near the Coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> according to General <hi>Monk</hi>'s and Viceadmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Pen</hi>'s Account, ſunk 30 of their Men of War, and took 1000 Priſoners, whereof Viceadmiral <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id.</hi> p. 544.</note> 
               <hi>Evertſon</hi> was one, and killed about 3000, whereof <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id.</hi> p. 545.</note> 
               <hi>Vantrump</hi> the Admiral was one. The <hi>Dutch</hi> owned to have loſt 27 Men of War in this Fight, and 6000 men; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> loſt but two Ships, and about 250 men. And in the firſt <hi>Dutch</hi> War after the Reſtauration, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> under the Conduct of his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> ſunk
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66038:30"/> and deſtroyed 20 of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, and blew up Admiral <hi>Opdam,</hi> with little loſs on our ſide. Theſe few Inſtances, Doctor, are enough to ſhew you, that there have been many greater Victories at Sea, than this laſt of ours, and I hope they will teach you hereafter to ſpeak juſtly and ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quately to your Subject, which <hi>Longinus</hi> makes one of the <hi>Characters</hi> of true Eloquence, and I believe it will go a great way in the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>honeſt</hi> man.</p>
            <p n="18">18. I cannot alſo but obſerve, how many and great things you ſay of our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> page 29, 30. becauſe you thought it <hi>no Deleverance</hi> not long before you took the Oath. To uſe your own Words againſt you, page 31. you thought it then a <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Calamity</hi> to be <hi>ſo</hi> delivered, and like a good Caſuiſt thought there might be ſome ways of <hi>Deliverance</hi> which a good man ought not to accept of; and <hi>ſome among our ſelves</hi> have heard you ſpeak of Generous and Heroic Heathens, who have choſen to dye, rather than to deliver themſelves by the Breach of their Oaths. Principles of ſtrict Honeſty and Juſtice went a great deal farther among them then, than they do now among <hi>ſome Chriſtians;</hi> and, as you in thoſe days would ſay, <hi>they ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt them, and condemn them:</hi> For then you could not ſee Wood for Trees, no more than <hi>thoſe Men,</hi> in ſeeing you could not ſee this great and bleſſed <hi>Deliverance,</hi> nor underſtand it; and therefore, Doctor, it did not become you to reflect upon them who remain in an Errour which held you ſo long captive; your buſineſs ſhould be to convince them, and to provoke them, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them with ſoft Words and hard Arguments; but on the contrary you reproach them and revile them, telling the World, page 32. <hi>That they invite the</hi> French <hi>to conquer them, and to place a zealous Papiſt, and arbitrary Prince upon the Throne.</hi> Certainly, Doctor, never man made ſo many rods for his own back, as you do in all your Writings on this unhappy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie: For how long is it ſince you would have rejoiced to ſee this Prince upon his Throne again, and would have had the <hi>Miracle</hi> done, though <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Mahomet</hi> had done it? Is he more <hi>popiſh</hi> or <hi>arbitrary</hi> now than He was then? Or is it not as lawfull now as it was then to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the King and the Papiſt, and between the <hi>French,</hi> as <hi>French,</hi> and as the Allies of King <hi>James?</hi> The <hi>Dutch</hi> are a People that all the World knows have done the <hi>Engliſh</hi> forty times more and greater Injuries than the <hi>French</hi> have done; and yet we could, when time ſerved, and ſtill do diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Dutch</hi> as <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> as our Friends and Allies: And by conſequence it would be falſe Logick, and a foul Reflexion upon ſome, to ſay <hi>that they invited</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> to conquer us. Well, but <hi>your meaning is, that you wonder that any</hi> Engliſh <hi>Proteſtants ſhould invite the</hi> French <hi>to place King</hi> James <hi>in his Throne again:</hi> For my part I know no ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants as invite the <hi>French</hi> upon any ſcore; but Have you not left King <hi>James</hi> the legal Right to the Throne? And do not you allow him to proſecute it, and recover it if he can? And doth not the Law, from which, as you grant, he hath his Right to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and recover, permit him alſo to ſeek Aid from the <hi>French,</hi> as well
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66038:30"/> as from the <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>Spaniards?</hi> And I dare ſay, if theſe would bring him in, it would be all one to him, and to you too. Ay, but the <hi>French</hi> are Papiſts: And was not the laſt Pope but one a <hi>Papiſt?</hi> And was not <hi>S</hi> — privately ſent to him; and did not he ſend a <hi>Nuncio</hi> privately hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And are not the <hi>Spaniards Inquiſition-Papiſts?</hi> Or did the <hi>French</hi> ever do ſo baſe a thing, as to ſay they were <hi>French,</hi> and no <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> or have they not as much natural Humanity, as any other men? But they are arbitrary Maſters: But what have we to doe with them as Maſters? And do not thoſe that have to doe with them, find them as good Maſters as ſome find their Neighbours? And come, Doctor, tell me plainly, would you not accept of Help from the <hi>French,</hi> if you ſtood in need of it? Nay, Would you not onely accept of it, but be very glad of it too? And therefore can you blame your old Maſter, if he ſeeks for Help from <hi>France,</hi> ſince you to recover much leſs than Three Kingdoms would doe the ſame thing. If he had choice of Aſſiſtance you might have ſome colour to blame him for accepting of <hi>French</hi> Help, and be angry with thoſe who conſider the <hi>French</hi> as his <hi>Allies.</hi> But here, Doctor, lies the Secret of your Diſpleaſure: It is not the <hi>French</hi> as <hi>French,</hi> or any other thing, but as King <hi>James</hi>'s Friends and Allies, that you and other Men hate them. You are affraid of him, and would hate the <hi>Dutch</hi> as well as the <hi>French,</hi> if they were his Friends: And the reaſon why you hate him is not that he is <hi>popiſh</hi> or <hi>arbitrary,</hi> but becauſe if he recover his Throne you will loſe your Chair. This, Doctor, is the hidden but true Reſource of all the Venom you diſgorge upon him and the <hi>French:</hi> You know you have ſinned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> like the <hi>Trumpeter</hi> in the <note n="*" place="margin">In Sir <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange</hi>'s <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fables.</note> Fable, which with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion upon it I recommend to your <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> could you have been ſecured of Pardon, and <hi>more Preferment</hi> upon his Reſtoration, I believe you would never have written your two Letters againſt the <hi>French</hi> Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nor have done the part of <hi>Shimei</hi> and <hi>Milton</hi> againſt him, as you have lately done. It is obſerved for your Honour, that neither you nor the other Pamphietiers preach'd or publiſhed one word againſt him before our late Victory over the <hi>French</hi> Fleet; and I am confident, if they had been victorious, the World had never ſeen your <hi>Temple</hi> Sermon, nor Letters, nor <hi>the Pretences of the</hi> French <hi>Invaſion examined,</hi> by <hi>that</hi> or any other hand. On the contrary, we ſhould have had Books and Sermons of another make, and to another Tune, from the ſame Quarter, and Apologies for King <hi>James,</hi> and the moſt arbitrary of his Proceedings, upon thoſe very To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks, from which (p. 23, 24, 25, 26.) you ſhew in three particulars how needfull it is to pray for Kings. I would to God, Doctor, you would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly read them over again, and apply them to your old Maſter; and if you will doe ſo, I heartily pray God, that while you read and ſo apply them, he would pour out upon you the Spirit of Prayer and Supplication, that you may look upon him whom you have pierced, and mourn for him, and all the Evils you have done againſt him as one mourneth for his onely Son.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66038:31"/>
            <p>The laſt thing I obſerve is a Contradiction of what you ſay, p. 27. by what you ſay in p. 29. In the former place you truly tell us, That <hi>No Prince can take our Religion from us, if we reſolve to keep it; but they may diſturb the Quiet and peaceable Enjoyment of it; which was the ſtate of the Church under the Heathen and perſecuting Emperours.</hi> This, Doctor, looks like ſomething ſpoken by the <hi>Author of Chriſtian Prudence,</hi> or one of thoſe Men who diſtinguiſh between Religion and the Externals of Religion, to ſhew the Fallacies and Diſ-ingenuity of others, that will not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between our Religion, and the <hi>Peace, Profit,</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> which by Law attend the Profeſſion and Adminiſtration of it. But then you forget your ſelf again, and run into this modiſh Fallacy in the latter place, where you tell us, That <hi>we owe our Religion to K.</hi> William, which cannot be true, if <hi>King</hi> James <hi>could not take it from us,</hi> as indeed he could not, let him have done the worſt you can imagine, if we had had the Faith and Conſtancy of the Church under the perſecuting Emperours: Had we followed their bleſſed Example, no Perſecution could have hurt our Religion; but like the Perſecutions in primitive Times, would have made it more auguſt and venerable, and eſtabliſhed it for ever; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is now evil ſpoken of for your ſakes, and ſeems to be drawing on to a fatal End in Theiſm, Atheiſm, Schiſms, Hereſies, and Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm, and an utter Contempt of the Clergy, of which you have as much reaſon to be ſenſible, as any other Man. But what need I to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this Contradiction in you, who have contradicted your ſelf ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that it will take up a great part of your Time and Thoughts to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> view, and cenſure your own Writings, and finally <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> what you will ſtand to, and what you <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and what you will have put in the collection of your <hi>Works,</hi> and what you will have left out of it. I know this is no acceptable Work to a great and haughty Writer; but, Doctor, it is a Work neceſſary to be done; and comfort gour ſelf with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the great St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and ſet about it preſently, while it is <hi>called day, leſt the Night come upon you, when you cannot work.</hi> You are bound in Honour and Conſcience to do it, and the World expects it from you, and will cenſure you when you are dead, if you leave it undone. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therefore, Doctor, which of your contradictory Pieces is fit to ſtand in the Collection of your <hi>Works,</hi> to declare your laſt Opinion of things: Muſt the Old <hi>Caſe of Nonreſiſtence.</hi> or the New <hi>Caſe of Allegiance</hi> make part of them? Will you ſtand by your <hi>Diſcourſe concerning the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion with him,</hi> and the <hi>Defence and Continuation of that diſcourſe;</hi> or will you ſtand by the Diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>the Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Communion of the Catholick Church,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Clegget</hi> told you was a flat Contradiction to the two former, and which you have been told again and again the Diſſenters make ill uſe of againſt the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Shall your Sermons before, or your Sermons ſince you took the Oath, make part of that Collection: By which of your two Faces will you be repreſented to Poſterity, the Face that looks back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66038:31"/> before your Apoſtacy, or the Face that looks forward ſince you Apoſtatized from your Principles? And will you finally ſtand to your <hi>Tritheiſtical</hi> Notion of the Trinity, which hath ſo expoſed you to the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> or will you retract it? Theſe are things, Doctor, that will require your moſt mature and ſerious Thoughts; and God grant, that you may ſo determine about them, as may be moſt for his Glory, the Honour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that of your own Memory in Ages to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the Dedication, page 1. line ult. after <hi>give</hi> inſert <hi>the Pope.</hi> In the Contents, § 7. l. 2. for <hi>is</hi> r. <hi>was,</hi> § 18. l. 4. for <hi>view</hi> r. <hi>review.</hi> In the Book, p. 1. l. 14. after <hi>believe</hi> dele the Semi colon, p. 2. l. 39. after <hi>as it was</hi> put a Comma, p. 5. l. 39. l. <hi>by</hi> r. <hi>in,</hi> p. 12. l. 26. r. <hi>reveal,</hi> l. 29. after <hi>for</hi> r. <hi>the Prayers of,</hi> p. 13. l. 40. r. <hi>perſiſt,</hi> p. 14. l. 14. r. <hi>Beliſarius.</hi> p. 19. l. 20. r. <hi>Moubray,</hi> p. 22. l. 12. for <hi>feared</hi> r. <hi>ſeared,</hi> l. 23. r. will <hi>ever</hi> be, p. 34. l. 19. l. <hi>Idols</hi> r. <hi>Gods,</hi> and for <hi>Kings</hi> r. <hi>Gods,</hi> p. 36. l. 5. r. to <hi>the</hi> Diſcretion, l: 36. r. CONSTANTIAL, p. 37. l. 6, f. <hi>Pomana</hi> r. <hi>Roma,</hi> l. 22. r. <hi>a little of his Skill in Coins,</hi> p. 38. l. 23. r. diſpute <hi>with,</hi> l. 31. r. <hi>commands,</hi> p. 39. l. 22. r. and <hi>that they are</hi> as.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
